<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The traveller's guide and the country's safety being a declaration of the laws of England against high-way-men or robbers upon the road : what is necessary and requisite to be done by such persons as are robbed in order to the recovering their damages : against whom they are to bring their action and the manner how it ought to be brought : illustrated with variety of law cases, historical remarks, customs, usages, antiquities and authentick authorities / by J.M.</title>
            <author>J. M.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 72 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A51818</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M50</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2818</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12412764</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12412764</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61578</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A51818)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61578)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 282:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The traveller's guide and the country's safety being a declaration of the laws of England against high-way-men or robbers upon the road : what is necessary and requisite to be done by such persons as are robbed in order to the recovering their damages : against whom they are to bring their action and the manner how it ought to be brought : illustrated with variety of law cases, historical remarks, customs, usages, antiquities and authentick authorities / by J.M.</title>
                  <author>J. M.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 127, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by the assigns of Richard and Edward Atkins, Esquires, for Langley Curtis ... and Thomas Simons ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [5] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Brigands and robbers --  Law and legislation --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61578:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61578:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Traveller's Guide,</hi> AND, <hi>The Country's Safety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BEING A Declaration of the Laws of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> againſt <hi>High-way-men,</hi> or <hi>Robbers upon the Road;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is neceſſary and requiſite to be done by ſuch perſons as are robbed in order to the recovering their damages;</p>
            <p>Againſt whom they are to bring their Action, and the manner how it ought to be brought.</p>
            <p>Illuſtrated with variety of Law Caſes, Hiſtorical Remarks, Cuſtoms, Uſages, Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities and Authentick Authorities.</p>
            <p>By <hi>J. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by the Aſſigns of <hi>Richard</hi> and <hi>Edward Atkins,</hi> Eſquires, for <hi>Langley Curtis,</hi> on <hi>Ludgate Hill,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Simons,</hi> at the <hi>Prince</hi>'s <hi>Arms</hi> in <hi>Ludgate Street,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:61578:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61578:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>TO travel the Road in ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is none of the leaſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages we receive by the Laws of <hi>England;</hi> for by them it is that we are protected from the violence of thoſe diſcontented, deſigning, profligate Wretches, the Robbers upon the High-way; fellows by their own Heraldry intitling themſelves <hi>Gentlemen of the Road,</hi> and glory in their invention of the moſt <hi>Gentile</hi> Trade of Ruining Mankind; when, alas, if you look into their <hi>Pedigree,</hi> you will find them ſo
<pb facs="tcp:61578:3"/>far from men of Honour or Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, that nothing can be made of them but a pack of idle diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Raſcals, the beſt of them but <hi>Cadets,</hi> moſt commonly the ſpawn of broken Tradeſmen and worſt of <hi>Debauchees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we deſign not ſo much by this Treatiſe to give the <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter</hi> of theſe <hi>Diſturbers</hi> of the Quiet and Repoſe of <hi>Mankind,</hi> as to ſet forth what good and wholſome Laws have been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly made by our diſcerning <hi>Anceſtours</hi> againſt them, and how the honeſt <hi>Traveller</hi> may obtain a <hi>Legal Recompence</hi> for the Loſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes he ſuſtains by ſuch Cattel; The main ſcope and intent of this Diſcourſe being to ſhew,</p>
            <p>That, whereas by the Statute of <hi>Winton,</hi> made in the Thirteenth year of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt, If divers
<pb facs="tcp:61578:3"/>perſons had committed a Robbery, the Hundred ſhould have been amerced, if they had not apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded all the Felons; and how that by the Statute of the Seven and Twentieth of <hi>Eliz.</hi> Chap. 13. a new Law is made in theſe points fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. None ſhall have an Action upon the ſaid Statute 13 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. except that the party robbed, doth give notice, as ſoon as he can, of the ſaid Felony, to ſome of the Inhabitants of ſome Town, Village or Hamlet, next to the place where the Robbery was done.</item>
               <item>2. If they in their purſuit ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend any of the Offenders, That ſhall excuſe them, although that they do not apprehend them all.</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:61578:4"/>
            <p>To which is added, for the benefit of Clerks and Attorneys, variety of Precedents, from the Declaration to the Execution, in all Caſes relating to the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Hundred where the party is robbed, that nothing may be wanting to compleat a Work ſo profitable both to the Attorney and his Client.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. M.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:61578:4"/>
            <head>THE TABLE.</head>
            <list>
               <item>RObbery, what it is. <hi>fol. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Where and how the party is to have reſtitution of the Goods where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he was robbed, upon an Appeal or Indictment. <hi>fol. 6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Action upon the Statute of <hi>Winton</hi> againſt the Hundred <hi>fol. 14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Where and how notice is to be given of the Robbery. <hi>fol. 25.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>At what time the Robbery muſt be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to charge the Hundred by an Action upon the Statute of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton. fol. 32.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>In what place a Robbery muſt be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to charge the Hundred: <hi>fol. 42.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How one or more againſt whom Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
<pb facs="tcp:61578:5"/>is had may have contribution from the reſt of the Inhabitants of the ſame Hundred. <hi>fol. 48.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Hue and Cry. <hi>fol. 66.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Who may raiſe the Hue and Cry, and for what cauſe. <hi>fol. 68.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How and in what manner the freſh ſuit and purſuit is to be made upon a Hue and Cry levied. <hi>fol. 74.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Who are bound to purſue upon the Hue and Cry levied. <hi>fol. 81.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Statute of <hi>Weſtminſter 1.</hi> Cap. <hi>9. Anno 3 Ed. 1.</hi> of Robberies. <hi>fol. 86.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Statute of <hi>Winton Anno 13 Ed. 1.</hi> of Robberies. <hi>fol. 88.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Proclamation or Writ directed to the Sheriff <hi>Anno 21 Ed. 1.</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim the Statute of <hi>Winton. fol. 91.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Statute of <hi>28 Ed. 3.</hi> Cap. <hi>11. fol. 94.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Statute of <hi>27 Eliz.</hi> Cap. <hi>11.</hi> Of Hue and Cry. <hi>fol. 97.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Form of an original Writ upon the Statute of Hue and Cry. <hi>fol. 111.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Retorn of the ſame Writ. <hi>fol. 115.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Declaration upon the ſame. <hi>fol. 116.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Aliter in Diviſis Hundredorum. fol. 117.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>General Iſſue pleaded with challenge to the Hundred. <hi>fol. 118.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:61578:5"/>
               <item>Barr, that no Hue and Cry was made. <hi>fol. 119.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Non inform'</hi> to a Declaration upon the Statute, with Judgment after a Writ of Inquiry. <hi>fol. 120.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Judgment upon the Statute after Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict. <hi>fol. 122.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Venire Facias. fol. 123.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Diſtringas</hi> againſt the Jury, with the Retorn. <hi>fol. ibid.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Writ of Inquiry. <hi>fol. 124.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Oath to be taken before a Juſtice of Peace by the perſon or perſons who are robbed, whereupon the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty robbed may ground his Action ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Statute of <hi>27 Eliz. fol. 126.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:61578:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61578:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> Traveller's Guide, <hi>AND,</hi> The Country's Safety.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>What is Robbery.</head>
               <p>RObbery is the felonious ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of any thing from the perſon of another againſt his will, whereby the perſon is put in fear; though the thing taken be but to the value of a peny, for which the Offender ſhall be hanged.</p>
               <p>Yet in ſome caſes it is not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that the thing whereof the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is robbed be actually taken from his perſon, for if the Robbers ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it by force and menaces, though the owner himſelf delivers it to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:61578:7"/>them, yet this tantamounts to a ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king from the perſon; for the Law reſpects the original cauſe <hi>(viz.)</hi> the threats and menaces which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated the Propriator to quit his goods for the preſervation of his life and perſon; As if one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand another preſently to deliver him his purſe, or otherwiſe he will kill him, which he does according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, this is Robbery, for the danger he confeſſed himſelf to be in by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of thoſe threatnings was the cauſe and motive of that delivery; So if two or more take a man and by force compell him to take an Oath to bring them ſuch a ſum of money, and if he does not they threaten to kill him; Though he brings it in purſuance of his Oath, and delivers it to them and they take it, yet this is Robbery, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that by this inforced Oath he was not bound in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to bring them the money; for he took it for fear of death, and ſo not voluntarily; If Felons come in the night to rob me in my houſe, and I, fearing leſt they ſhould enter
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:61578:7"/>the houſe and rob me, and, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent their entry, I throw money or plate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> out at the window to them,<note place="margin">44 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3.14.</note> which they take and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, this is Robbery; for, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Law, it is the ſame as if they had taken it from my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>If Felons take goods openly in a place where the Owner is preſent, and thereby put him in fear, or take his horſe or drive his cattel out of his paſture or fold, he ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by and looking on them,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>22</hi> Aſſ p. <hi>39.</hi> Fit. Car. <hi>115.</hi>
                  </note> ſo that he be terrified by their vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent carriage, menaces, aſſaults or otherwiſe, this is Robbery in the takers, and the Law ſuppoſes it to be done with ſuch violence that he is not able nor dare not to reſiſt them, <hi>&amp; in privata cauſa nemo tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur exponere ſe periculis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The putting the party in fear is an eſpecial part of a Robbery, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, in eſtimation of Law, no Robbery can be committed;<note place="margin">5 <hi>Eliz. Dier</hi> 224.</note> for if I be travelling upon the road, and one comes by and takes my money from my pocket, or my ſword from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61578:8"/>my ſide unknown to me, this is Felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but no Robbery.</p>
               <p>The taking away of ſomething from the perſon, either in Fact or Law, is as neceſſary an ingredient to make a Robbery as the Putting of the party in fear; As if one lies in wait in the high-way to rob paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, and he bids a Traveller which comes along to ſtand and yield him his purſe,<note place="margin">9 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.26.</note> if the Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler upon reſiſtance overcome him, and either apprehends him or puts him to flight, though there was a deſign and an attempt to commit a Robbery, yet, <hi>volunt as non reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur pro facto,</hi> and though the Law adjudges this intent to be no Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, yet it ranks it, and that not undeſerved, amongſt the higheſt of miſdemeanours.</p>
               <p>So that the difference betwixt Robbery and a Theft is that, That one is done openly and with force, the other ſecretly and ſurreptitiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; And if any thing be taken from a man openly and in his preſence, and his perſon is not thereby put in fear, this amounts onely to a treſpaſs.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:61578:8"/>
               <p>A Traveller may juſtifie the kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of any perſon who ſhall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to rob or murther him upon the way, and that without the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture of either lands, goods or chattels;<note place="margin">22 <hi>Aſſ.</hi> 55.26 <hi>Aſſ. p.</hi> 23. <hi>&amp;</hi> 32. <hi>Co.</hi> li. 5.91. <hi>Fit. Coron.</hi> 30. <hi>&amp;</hi> 305.</note> This point of the forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was ſomewhat diſputable at the Common Law; Some would have it to be the ſame with killing of a man by chance-medly, or <hi>ſe defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo;</hi> but this point hath been cleared by an explanatory Act made in the 24 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. where it is declared, <hi>That if any perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons do attempt feloniouſly to rob or murther any perſon or perſons in or nigh any common high-way, cart-way, horſe-way or foot-way, and if any ſuch evil diſpoſed perſon happen to be kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led or ſlain in ſuch attempt, and he that ſo killed him be thereof indicted or appealed, That the perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo indicted or appealed, and of the ſame by verdict ſo found and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhall not forfeit or loſe any lands, tenements, goods or chattels, for the death of any ſuch evil diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed perſon in ſuch manner ſlain, but ſhall be thereof and for the ſame fully
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61578:9"/>acquitted and diſcharged, in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as the ſame perſon or perſons ſhould be, if he or they were lawfully acquitted of the death of ſuch evil diſpoſed perſon or perſons.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Where and how the party is to have reſtitution of the goods whereof he was robbed, upon an Appeal or Indictment.</head>
               <p>AT the Common Law, before the Statute of <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> the perſon robbed had no other ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction but onely reſtitution of his goods, in caſe he made freſh pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit after the Robber, and convic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him at his own Suit <hi>(viz.)</hi> by an Appeal of Robbery. The Law is ſo eager to have Felons apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that if the party does not uſe his utmoſt endeavours to get the Offender taken, it puniſheth him with the loſs and forfeiture of the goods ſtolen; So that if the Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor be convicted at the Suit of the party, yet if the Jury does not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61578:9"/>find that he had made freſh ſuit af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Felon, the goods ſtoln are forfeited to the King, and no reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution can be made of them.</p>
               <p>As the Law condemns the not purſuing or in ſlack and faint pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit of Robbers; ſo it rewardeth diligent endeavours though they meet with no ſucceſs: for if a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon which committed a Robbery be not taken by the ſpace of a year after the Felony committed, yet if the party that was robbed doe his endeavour to apprehend the Felon, and make diligent and ſpecial en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry for him, and after he be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, though not at the ſuit of the party robbed, yet that ſhall be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged a ſufficient freſh ſuit, and upon his appeal brought, and the Offender convicted, he ſhall have reſtitution of his goods robbed; and if this freſh ſuit was made by a Servant, and not by the party rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed himſelf, it is ſufficient to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him reſtitution.</p>
               <p>Conviction without Attainder is ſufficient to entitle the Appealant to a reſtitution, though in ancient
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61578:10"/>times ſome opinions have been to the contrary, and that no reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion could be made untill after at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainder, and in ſome caſes where no attainder could be (as where the Felon died in priſon before the Owner had commenced his appeal) though the ſuit was never ſo freſh, <hi>Fit. Coron.</hi> 319.8 <hi>E.</hi> 3.10. But now it is agreed that if after the appeal commenced the Felon die in priſon or break the priſon, the freſh ſuit ſhall be enquired, and if found, the party robbed ſhall be reſtored to his goods, <hi>Fit. Coron.</hi> 379. 26 <hi>Aſſ. p.</hi> 32. So if the Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor ſtand mute or challenge per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emptorily above the number which the Law does allow, or demand his Clergy, in every of theſe caſes the freſh ſuit being found by inqueſt, the Appealant ſhall have reſtitution of his goods, for he had done all that he could in order to an attainder.</p>
               <p>If an appeal of Robbery be ſued againſt the Principal and Acceſſory, and the Principal be attainted and the freſh ſuit is ſound, reſtitution ſhall be made of the ſtoln goods
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61578:10"/>without proſecuting the ſuit againſt the Acceſſory, and yet his continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the ſuit againſt the Acceſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhall not hinder his reſtitution, for that the principal Felon is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted by his procurement; and the Appealant ſhall have reſtitution whether the Acceſſory be attainted or acquitted; In the ſame manner the Appealant ſhall have reſtitution where he ſues an appeal againſt two as Principals and one of them is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitted, 21. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.16. 10 <hi>H.</hi> 4.5. If one man rob divers men, for which they bring their ſeveral ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peals, and the Felon is attainted at the ſuit of one of them, and the freſh ſuit is found, in this caſe the reſt ſhall not have reſtitution untill the Offender be convicted at their ſeveral ſuits, and likewiſe the freſh ſuit ſeverally found.</p>
               <p>There are ſome opinions which hold that if the Appealant ſue the Robber to the outlawry that he ſhall have reſtitution of his goods without enquiring of the freſh ſuit, for that he had proſecuted againſt the Appealee as far as the Law gave him way.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:61578:11"/>
               <p>An enquiry muſt be made of the freſh ſuit before any reſtitution can be awarded; and that too before the Juſtices and not the Sheriff, and by the Jury that convicted the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendant of the Robbery: But in caſe the Defendant doth confeſs the appeal, then it muſt be enquired of by a <hi>Viſne</hi> from that County where the Robbery was committed, and where the appeal is brought, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be brought in <hi>London;</hi> for that the City hath a privilege not to be forced to appear upon Juries out of the City; And it cannot be taken there by <hi>Niſi Prius,</hi> becauſe it is but an inqueſt of Office; Therefore in this caſe the <hi>Viſne</hi> ſhall come from that County where the Robber was taken, and ſo it ſhall be enquired by the people of that County.</p>
               <p>In the firſt place the Court is to ask the Defendant in the appeal if he claims any property in the goods; which if he ſays he does not, then it muſt be enquired if the goods were the Plaintiff's at the time of the Robbery committed,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61578:11"/>and alſo enquire of the freſh ſuit.</p>
               <p>If the Manner (<hi>viz.</hi> the ſtoln goods) wherewith the Felon is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken be portable, or that it can be otherwiſe done with conveniency, it ought to be brought into the Court before the Juſtices, and if it be in a trunk, box, cheſt or cloak-bag, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Appealant muſt tell particularly what goods there are in it before it be opened, or that he can have reſtitution.</p>
               <p>The Appealant's freſh ſuit being found by the Inqueſt, the Court ought to award him reſtitution of all the goods contained in his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal, which the King's Officers or any other had ſeiſed to the King's uſe.</p>
               <p>Having ſhewed how the party robbed might obtain reſtitution of his goods by Appeal, in the next place falls under conſideration the caſe of an Indictment: At Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, if the perſon robbed had ſteered his courſe this way he had certainly ſplit himſelf upon the rocks; for reſtitution could in no
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61578:12"/>caſe be awarded upon an Indictment, though the Jury that found the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender guilty of the Robbery had likewiſe found the freſh Suit. To remedy this inconveniency an Act was made 21 <hi>H.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 18. whereby it was enacted, <hi>That if any Felon or Felons do rob or take away money, goods or chattels from any of the King's Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, from their perſon or otherwiſe within this Realm, and thereof the ſaid Felon or Felons be indicted, and after arraigned of the ſame Felony and found guilty thereof, or otherwiſe attainted by reaſon of evidence given by the party robbedd or owner of the ſaid money, goods and chattels, that as well Juſtices of Goal delivery, as other Juſtices before whom any ſuch Felon or Felons ſhall be found guilty or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe attainted by reaſon of evidence given by the party ſo robbed or owner, or by any other by their procurement, have power by this Act to award from time to time Writs of reſtitution for the ſaid money, goods or chattels in like manner as though any ſuch Felon or Felons were attainted at the Suit of the party in appeal:</hi> So that by
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61578:12"/>virtue of this Act the party robbed may have reſtitution upon evidence given by himſelf or by any other by his procurement notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that he made not any freſh Suit.</p>
               <p>If the Servant be robbed of his Maſter's goods, the Maſter may give evidence againſt the Felon by virtue of theſe words <hi>(the party ſo robbed or owner)</hi> And if the party robbed does not give evidence him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf but procure another to doe it, this is ſufficient within the words of the Statute to enable him to obtain reſtitution.</p>
               <p>If one man do rob goods from three men ſeverally, and he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted for the robbing of one of them, and thereupon arraigned; though the other two would give evidence againſt the Malefactor, yet they ſhall not have reſtitution of their goods within the intent and meaning of this Act, for the Felon is not attainted of any other Robbery but that whereof he is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted: But if he be indicted of all the three ſeveral Robberies ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61578:13"/>and arraigned upon one of them, and convicted upon the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence given by one of the parties robbed, yet he ſhall be after ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigned upon the other two Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that he may be alſo found guilty by the evidence of the other two perſons robbed; to the end they may have reſtitution of their goods.</p>
               <p>Though this Statute ſpeak onely of the party robbed, yet his Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors and Adminiſtrators are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the meaning of it: for it is a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial Law, and gives a more ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy remedy to the party robbed than the Common Law gave by way of Indictment, and therefore ought to be conſtrued beneficially.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of the Action upon the Statute of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> againſt the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.</head>
               <p>HAving ſhewed how and in what caſes the party robbed may have reſtitution of the ſtoln goods,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61578:13"/>both upon an Appeal and an Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, now I ſhall proceed to ſhew what further remedy the Law gives him for his indempnity. At Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law, if a man was robbed, he was preſently to uſe his utmoſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to apprehend the Felon, and if he was found defective or negligent in this particular, the Law would give him no relief; and though there was no neglect in him, yet for want of the due and ſpeedy aſſiſtance of others, which were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliged to joyn with him in the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit, perhaps the Robber was not taken untill ſuch time as he had op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to make away and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bezle the goods; So that if it chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced that he was taken afterwards, the party was deſtitute of any ſort of recompence, whereas if the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon had been freſhly and vigorouſly purſued from Town to Town, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as the Law does direct and require, he might have been taken with the Manner, and upon an Appeal brought and a conviction there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, the Owner was to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the goods which were
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61578:14"/>ſtoln from him. It is true the Law did puniſh the Inhabitants of the place where the Robbery was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, if, upon notice given to the Conſtable of the Town, the Huy and Cry was not raiſed, and all perſons within the Town were bound to follow the purſuit, which if they did not they were puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by Fine and Impriſonment, this Cry was to be carried from Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable to Conſtable; and if any Town was indicted for the eſcape of the Felon, the purſuit with Huy and Cry to the next Conſtable was a good excuſe, a total neglect or at leaſt the faint and weak perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of theſe freſh ſuits being not duly puniſhed, Robbers did eſcape unpuniſhed, and that impunity was an encouragement to others to commit the like enormities, to the great and manifeſt danger of the King's Subjects travelling upon their lawfull occaſions. For the indemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of perſons who ſhould ſuſtain any loſs by Robberies, and for the more effectual obliging of Cities, Towns and Villages, and to diſcharge
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61578:14"/>their duty with great care and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in the purſuing and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending of Felons, it was thought fit a Law ſhould be made, that if the Felons were not taken within ſuch a time, the Hundred where the Robbery was committed ſhould ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the party whatever he was damnified thereby; to that end there was a Statute made at <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter,</hi> in the 13 <hi>E.</hi> 1. whereby, in the preamble thereof, is ſet forth the principal cauſe of the frequent eſcapes of Felons without being ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended, and why the Laws which were then extant proved ineffectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to ſuppreſs and extinguiſh both Felons and Felonies, and whence the growth of them proceeded, for that Felons could not be attainted by the Oaths of Jurors, who had rather ſtrangers ſhould be robbed and the Robbers eſcape puniſhment than indict the Offenders, of whom great part were of the ſame Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, or at leaſt, if the Offenders were of another Country, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farvors might be of places near; and they did this, becauſe no Oath
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61578:15"/>was given to the Jurors of the ſame Country where the Felonies were committed, and no Law obliged them to reſtitution of damages, nor any penalty limited for their concealment and Latches. And for that the fear of a penalty more than that of an Oath might be a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter engagement upon them not to ſpare or conceal Felonies, therefore it was enacted, 
<q>That if any Robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be committed (if need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires) Inqueſt ſhall be made in Towns by him that is Lord of the Town, and after in the Hundred, and in the Franches and in the County, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in two, three or four Counties, in caſe where Felonies ſhall be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Marches of Shires.</q>
And it was further enacted, 
<q>That if the Country will not anſwer for the Bodies of ſuch Offenders, the people of every ſuch Country ſhall be anſwerable for the Robberies and alſo the damages, ſo that the whole Hundred, with the Franchiſes being within the precincts of the ſame Hundred, ſhall be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for the Robberies done. And if the Robbery be done in the diviſions
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61578:15"/>of two Hundreds, both the Hundreds and the Franchiſes within the ſame ſhall be anſwerable; And after the Robbery be done, the Country ſhall have no longer ſpace than half a year, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in which time it ſhall behoove them to agree for the Robbery or Offence, or elſe that they ſhall anſwer for the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of the Offenders.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But afterwards by another Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute made <hi>An.</hi> 28 <hi>E.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 11. it is ordained 
<q>That the Country ſhall have no longer term after the Robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry committed than forty days, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in which time they muſt make ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for the Robbery or anſwer the Bodies of the Felons.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The perſon robbed ſhall have an Action upon the Statute of <hi>Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> againſt the Hundred, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that the Statute does not expreſly mention any Action; for when it ſays the Hundred ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for the Robbery and the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages; the Hundred within the meaning of the Statute is to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the party robbed; for he is the perſon damnified and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to be relieved within this
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61578:16"/>Act; and when the Statute gives him recompence or ſatisfaction for the loſs he had ſuſtained by the Robbery, the Law by implication gives him the neceſſary means whereby he is to attain to it, and that is an Action to be grounded upon this Statute. Proceſs and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution againſt the Hundred, I ſhall ſpeak of at large in another place.</p>
               <p>By the two aforeſaid Statutes of the 13 <hi>E.</hi> 1. made at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> li. 7. ſo. 7.</note> and the 28 <hi>E.</hi> 3. the Country, if it did not anſwer for the Bodies of all the Offenders, muſt of neceſſity have made ſatisfaction for the Robbery, though (in caſe it was done by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny) ſome of the Felons upon pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit had been taken; but this is moderated by a Clauſe in the 27 <hi>El. cap.</hi> 13. whereby it is enacted, <q>If any Robbery be committed by two or more, and any one of them be appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended upon ſuch purſuit as the Law does require, that no Hundred or Franches ſhall incurr the penalty or loſs or forfeiture mentioned in this Statute of the <hi>27 El.</hi> or any of the two
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61578:16"/>former Statutes, though the reſt of the Felons make their eſcape.</q>
               </p>
               <p>The party robbed was not limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to any time within which he ſhould bring his Action before the 27 <hi>El.</hi> which Act does provide, <q>That no perſon or perſons robbed ſhall take advantage by virtue of any fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Act, to charge any Hundred where any robbery ſhall be committed, unleſs he or they ſo robbed ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence his or their Suit or Action with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in one year next after ſuch Robbery ſo committed;</q> for if the Robbery be committed upon the firſt of <hi>May,</hi> and the original bear teſt the firſt of <hi>May</hi> following the Action does not lie, for it muſt of neceſſity be commenced within the year.</p>
               <p>This Statute of the 27 <hi>El.</hi> doth likewiſe bind the perſon robbed to the performance of ſome conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons before he can be enabled to bring his Action, for the Act ſays, <q>That no perſon or perſons robbed, ſhall maintain any action of the two fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Statutes, except the ſaid perſon or perſons ſo robbed, ſhall, with as much convenient ſpeed as may be,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61578:17"/>give notice of the ſame Robbery ſo committed unto ſome of the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of ſome Town, Village or Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let near unto the place where ſuch Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery was committed; Nor ſhall by virtue of the Statutes aforeſaid bring any Action unleſs he or they ſhall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in twenty days next before ſuch Action to be brought, be examined upon his or their corporal Oaths to be taken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome one Juſtice of the Peace of the County where the Robbery was committed, inhabiting within the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred where the ſaid Robbery was done or near unto the ſame, whether he or they know the parties that committed the Robbery or any of them. And if upon examination it be confeſſed that he or they do know the parties that did the Robbery, or any of them, then he or they ſo confeſſing, ſhall, before the ſaid Action be commenced enter into a Recognizance before the ſaid Juſtice to proſecute the ſaid perſon or perſons ſo known to have committed the Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery by Indictment or otherwiſe, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the due courſe of the Laws of this Realm.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:61578:17"/>
               <p>So that theſe four things are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary;
<list>
                     <item>1. That notice with all convenient ſpeed be given to the Inhabitants of the place near where the Robbery was done.</item>
                     <item>2. That the ſaid Oath be taken be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Juſtice of the Peace within twenty days next before the Action commenced.</item>
                     <item>3. That he enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Recognizance to proſecute the Felons in caſe he knows any of them.</item>
                     <item>4. That the Action it ſelf be brought within a year after the Robbery committed.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>If the Servant be robbed of his Maſter's goods, the Servant is to give the notice to the Inhabitants, for he is beſt able to deſcribe the Felons, and give information which way they are gone; ſo that the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try by his directions may the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter purſue and deſcry the Malefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, and the Oath required by the Statute, made by him is ſufficient, becauſe the contents of the Oath is, <hi>Whether the party robbed knew any of the Offenders?</hi> and a knowledge of the Robbers (within the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Act) is expected from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61578:18"/>none but the perſon that was rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed.</p>
               <p>The Servant is likewiſe the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to be bound in the Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance, the Statute requires that, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe no perſon is ſuppoſed fitter to give evidence againſt the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders than he that was robbed by them. But the Action againſt the Hundred muſt be brought by the Maſter, for he is the Propriator: but if the Servant refuſes to make the Oath, or enter into the Recog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance before the Juſtice, <hi>Quaere,</hi> What remedy the Maſter hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him?</p>
               <p>If a man be robbed in the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred of <hi>A.</hi> in the County of <hi>B.</hi> and he that was robbed takes the Oath injoyned by this Act before a Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Peace inhabiting in or near the Hundred of <hi>A.</hi> at any place out of the County of <hi>B.</hi> the Oath ſo taken hath been adjudged ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to entitle him to his Action, for by virtue of this Act he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th a ſpecial power (which is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined to any place) to adminiſter this Oath whereever he be, and it
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61578:18"/>is not like that authority which he derives from his Commiſſion, which is local, and can be exerciſed no where elſe beſides in the County where he is conſtituted Juſtice of the Peace.</p>
               <p>If ſeveral men be robbed at one time and place, the number of their Actions to be brought againſt the Hundred depends upon the quality of the property they had in the goods whereof they were robbed; for if they had ſeveral properties they muſt bring ſeveral Actions,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dier</hi> 370. pl. 59.</note> but if they be joint Owners or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietors then they muſt all join in one Action, or ſo many of them as are ſo jointly poſſeſſed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Where and how notice is to be given of the Robbery.</head>
               <p>IT appears by the Statute of <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> the 1ſt, made in the third year of <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt, That at
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61578:19"/>Common Law 'twas the duty of the Inhabitants to keep and guard the Country from Thefts and Robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in caſe any Felony was committed they were to purſue and apprehend the Felons, otherwiſe they were puniſhable for the eſcape of ſuch Offenders: every Town was obliged at its peril to take notice of any Robbery committed within its precincts, though done (if in the day time) in a place never ſo ſecret;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dier</hi> 210. pl. 25.</note> as if a man be ſlain in the Fields or Lane or any other private place belonging to the Town, if the Murtherer eſcape untaken, the Town was amerceable, though the Inhabitants thereof had not the leaſt knowledge of it, for in many caſes the Law doth preſume a know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as the Jury that is to try an Iſſue is ſuppoſed to have recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of the matter of fact in Iſſue between the parties; So if one be outlawed of Felony in the County-Court, and afterwards is received by any perſon of the ſame County, that receipt makes him acceſſary to the Felony, for the Law believes
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61578:19"/>no man, reſiding in the ſame Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to be ignorant of what is tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted in that Court; to which ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally every one owes ſuit and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance. Likewiſe if one retain my Servant in the ſame County where I live, if I bring an Action againſt him for ſo doing, his igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the fact in this caſe does not excuſe him, for he is bound to take notice of the firſt retainder, but if he retains my Servant in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother County, then the Law is otherwiſe; So alſo a man is bound to take notice of all Acts done up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his own freehold. The Statute of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> which give the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt the Hundred, is general, and does not ſpecifie any time or place when or where the Robbery is to be done, which makes the Hundred liable, yet the Sages of the Law have put ſuch a conſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon the general words of that Statute, that the Robbery, which binds the Country to render ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to the party robbed, muſt be committed in the day-time, and not in the night, and not in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61578:20"/>place as a Houſe, but openly, ſo that the Country may take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of it themſelves,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> li. 7. ſo. 7.</note> for it was not neceſſary for him that was robbed to levy any Huy and Cry, or give any notice of the Robbery to the Inhabitants of the Country, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the letter of the foreſaid Statute of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> or by the meaning of it; for it may be that the perſon robbed was bound or maimed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo that he could not raiſe any Huy and Cry or give any notice to the Country, and it is a general Rule in Law, that where the Law appoints no perſon to give notice, the party concerned himſelf is bound to take notice at his peril; as if a Church becomes void, by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Statute of the 21ſt. of <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. the Patron is bound to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent at his peril within, ſix months after the inſtitution and induction into the ſecond Benefice,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cro.</hi> par. 1.258.</note> though all this be done without his having the leaſt knowledge of it.<note place="margin">Dier <hi>292.</hi>
                  </note> But if a Church becomes void by ſentence of deprivation in the Eccleſiaſtical Court, and the ſix months after
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61578:20"/>which the elapſe is to incurr, is to commence but from the time of ſuch notice given, and the reaſon of the firſt caſe is the Church being <hi>ipſo facto</hi> void, there being no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whom the Law requires to give the Patron notice of ſuch avoidance, he is obliged to take notice of it himſelf. If a Tenant in Fee-ſimple convey the Eſtate to the uſe of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for life, the remainder to his Wife for life, the remainder to his eldeſt Son in Fee, and afterwards enfeoffs <hi>A.</hi> with Warranty, and dies, the Wife and the Son enter upon <hi>A.</hi> and joyn in a Feoffment to <hi>B.</hi> the Heir being barred by the Warranty,<note place="margin">Cro. Car. <hi>393.</hi>
                  </note> this Feoffment is a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture of the Wife's Eſtate for life; for ſhe was to take cognizance of the ſaid Feoffment made by her Husband, becauſe the Livery is a publick and notorious Act, and ſhe ought at her peril to take notice of this Act done upon the Land, none being bound to give her notice of it.</p>
               <p>That this matter of the notice is now altered by the Statute of 27 <hi>El.</hi> whereby it is provided, <q>That no
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61578:21"/>perſon ſhall maintain any Action upon the Statute of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Statute, except the perſon robbed, with as much convenient ſpeed as may be, give notice of the Robbery to ſome of the Inhabitants of ſome Town, Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage or Hamlet near the place where ſuch Robbery ſhall be committed:</q> yet it is not neceſſary that notice be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to thoſe of the Hundred where the Robbery was done, but to the Inhabitants of any Village near ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning to the place where the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon was robbed,<note place="margin">Cro Car. <hi>379.</hi>
                  </note> though in another Hundred, for the Statute does not mention that notice be given to the Inhabitants of that Hundred where the Robbery was committed, and alſo by intendment the perſon rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed cannot know the diviſions of the Hundred; And though notice be given out of the County, yet it is well enough, provided he makes it in a Village near adjoyning to the place where he was robbed;<note place="margin">Cro. Car. <hi>41.</hi>
                  </note> As in an Action brought againſt the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of <hi>Dackorum</hi> and <hi>Caſhoe,</hi> the Plaintiff alledged the Robbery to be committed at <hi>Shealey</hi> and <hi>Ridge in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61578:21"/>diviſis Hundredorum de Dackorum &amp; Caſhoe in Com. Hertford,</hi> and that he gave notice of the Robbery at <hi>South Mims,</hi> in the County of <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſex,</hi> near the Hundreds aforeſaid, in this caſe the whole Court adjud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the notice given in <hi>Middleſex</hi> to be ſufficient, and that the party robbed is no more bound to know the diviſions of Counties than he is of Hundreds. And likewiſe not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding that the words of the Statute are, <hi>that notice be given near the place where the Robbery was,</hi> yet the Court held that this allegation of the notice given at <hi>South Mims,</hi> near the Hundreds aforeſaid, was well enough, and ſhall be intended in the diviſion where the Robbery was done; So if a Robbery be alledged to be committed <hi>in diviſis Hundre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorum,</hi> &amp;c. and notice given at ſuch a place,<note place="margin">New Book of <hi>Ent.</hi> ſo 348.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp;c. prope diviſis Hundredo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum praedict.</hi> &amp;c. it ſhall be inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be given in the diviſion of the Hundreds where the Robbery was done, and not in the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote place thereof, for that ſhould be a forein intendment, though it be
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:61578:22"/>good either way, yet it is beſt to alledge the notice to have been gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at the place where the Robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was committed, or at a Village near unto adjoyning.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>At what time the Robbery muſt be committed, to charge the Hundred by an Action upon the Statute of <hi>Wincheſter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THough the Statute of <hi>Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> as I have ſhewed you in the foregoing Chapter, is general, both as to time and place, and that it hath been expounded not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to any Robbery, unleſs the ſame be committed in the day-time,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> li. 7. fo. 7.</note> for of Felonies done in the night the Country of it ſelf is not bound to take notice, for they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conveniently purſue or make enquiry after the Offenders in the night-time; And ſince the Statute makes the Country anſwerable for
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61578:22"/>the Robbery, it were too hard to require from them a performance of that which they are deprived of the ordinary and convenient means to effect. This Statute was expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded according to the rule and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Common Law (as it may appear by the caſe of the 3d. of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3d. Tit. <hi>Coron.</hi> 293.) <q>That if a Murther or any other Felony be done in the night and the Malefactor eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, the Town was not to be amerced for it.</q>
               </p>
               <p>In this point of the time there is a difference between a purſuit for the King and for the party, upon the Statute, as ſhall be further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated hereafter, when I come to treat of Huy and Cry; though in neither caſe the Law does con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain the Country to take cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance at their peril of any Felony acted in the night:<note place="margin">2 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.8. B. 9. A</note> yet in caſe of a purſuit for the King, upon actual notice given of the Felony, the Law, upon Huy and Cry levied, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects the readineſs and uttermoſt diligence of the Inhabitants to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the Malefactors. As if a man
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61578:23"/>be robbed or aſſaulted and offered to be robbed, either in the day or night, if the perſon himſelf or any other reſort to the Conſtable of the Town, and acquaint him with the caſes, deſcribing the perſon, and giving information which way the Offender is gone, and require him to raiſe the Huy and Cry, it is the duty of the Conſtable to raiſe the power of the Town, as well in the night as in the day, for the proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Offender, and if he be not found, there to give warning to the next Conſtable, and he to the next, untill the Offender be taken.</p>
               <p>If a Traveller be robbed in the night, and gives notice to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable of the Village as aforeſaid, though the Conſtable is obliged (as I have ſaid already) to raiſe the Huy and Cry, yet this at the moſt is but a purſuit for the King, and the Traveller ſhall take no advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage of the negligence thereof, in caſe the Felons make their eſcape, for God hath ordained the day for man to labour and travel,<note place="margin">Co. ubi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</note> as a fit
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61578:23"/>time for him to exerciſe his indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, and the night for his repoſe and quietneſs, being tired and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with his daily operation; and accordingly the Law ſuppoſes eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſon in the night to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired himſelf from his labour to take his natural reſt, neither does the Law require his preſence or at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance upon his own private af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs,<note place="margin">12 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>tit.</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs 17.11 <hi>H.</hi> 7. fo. 5. Acc<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> nor allow an occaſion to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt or diſturb him in his ſleep. Therefore it hath been adjudged that a man cannot diſtrain in the night for a rent Service (becauſe the diſtreſs being in it ſelf a demand of the rent, which the Tenant ought to pay, whenſoever it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, upon the Land out of which it iſſues) for that the Law does not require his being upon the ground, nor his readineſs to tender his rent in the night as it does in the day-time. It is true,<note place="margin">10 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. fo. 21.</note> a man may diſtrain for damage Feaſant in the night, and the Law does allow it onely for the neceſſity of the caſe, for if the Owner of the Land ſhould permit the Cattel to continue there
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:61578:24"/>till morning, perhaps by that time they may eſtray out of the ground, and ſo they cannot be diſtrained at all, for they muſt be taken damage feaſant <hi>(viz.)</hi> doing of the treſpaſs upon the ground. Therefore ſince none are bound to have an eye in the night upon Thieves and Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers in the Country, it is both the intereſt and ſafety of our Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, that he take care not to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad at unſeaſonable hours, for then in ſome reſpect he is out of the protection of the Law, which makes no proviſion for his indemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity in caſe he be robbed, and the Poet further warns him of his dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t jugulent homines ſurgunt de nocte Latrones.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And whereas it is further provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Statute of <hi>Wincheſter, cap.</hi> 4. <hi>That in all Cities and great Towns which are walled the Gates be kept ſhut from Sun-ſetting to Sun-ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,</hi> I conceive that if a man be robbed in ſuch a City or Town,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61578:24"/>though it be done in the night, yet the Inhabitants ſhall anſwer for the Robbery, and notwithſtanding that at the Common Law no place was puniſhable for the eſcape of any Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon in the night, yet this Statute hath changed the reaſon and ground of that Law, and <hi>ratio Legis eſt ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Legis &amp; mutata Legis ratione mutatur &amp; Lex,</hi> for if they do not keep their Gates ſhut according to the Statute whereby the Felon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcapes, there is a default and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence in them, which renders them liable to puniſhment if the Felon be not apprehended by them, and it was adjudged in the 3d. of <hi>Ed.</hi> 3d. <hi>That where a man being ſlain within a wall'd Town in the night,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>tit.</hi> Coron. 299.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Murtherer eſcaped, that the whole Town ſhould be amerced, Quaere,</hi> Whether the caſe of the Robbery may not be within the ſame rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon?</p>
               <p>It is neceſſary that the Robbery, for which the County is to anſwer, be done in the day-time and out of the night, and if a man be robbed after Sun-ſet and before it be dark,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:61578:25"/>yet the Hundred is chargeable, as it was reſolved in an Action brought againſt the Inhabitants of <hi>Eveinger,</hi> by one <hi>Aſhpoole,</hi> who was robbed in <hi>January</hi> after Sun-ſet while it was day-light, and the Court gave Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the Plaintiff,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co</hi> li. 7. fo. 6.</note> for that it was a time convenient for men to travel and be about their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>And in another Action commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced againſt the Hundred of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> it was reſolved that for a Robbery done in the morning <hi>ante lucem</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> before it is light) the Hundred is not chargeable,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> ub. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra.</note> for that the Robbery is done in the night.</p>
               <p>In an Action upon the Statute of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> brought againſt the Hundred of <hi>Morely,</hi> the Jury found that the Robbery was done <hi>poſt lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem ejuſdem diei &amp; ante ortum Solis,</hi> that is, after day-break and before Sun-riſing, and it was adjudged the Plaintiff ſhould recover againſt the Hundred. So alſo a Robbery com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted <hi>poſt occaſum Solis &amp; per diur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam lucem,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cro. Jac. <hi>106.</hi>
                  </note> that is, after Sun-ſet
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:61578:25"/>and by day-light, was held good to charge the Country.</p>
               <p>The Hundred of <hi>Warrington,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſued upon the aforeſaid Statute for a Robbery committed, it was held by <hi>Anderſon</hi> and all the Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, that if a Robbery be done in the morning before day or in the evening after the day,<note place="margin">Cro. Eli. <hi>270.</hi>
                  </note> in any time of the night in which men uſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly to travel, that the Hundred is anſwerable for it. But if it be done at twelve or one of the Clock in the night, at which time every one is intended to be in bed, the Hundred is not bound to anſwer for the Robbery, <hi>Quaere</hi> of this Caſe, for it contradicts the forementio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Authorities, and the reaſons of them.</p>
               <p>Though in moſt caſes travelling upon the <hi>Sunday</hi> be prohibited and puniſhable by Law, yet if any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo travelling be robbed, the Country is not excuſable, as it was held by three Juſtices, in the caſe of one <hi>Wayte,</hi> againſt the Hundred of <hi>Stoke,</hi>

                  <q>That notwithſtanding a Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery be committed upon the Sunday in
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61578:26"/>the time of Divine Service, yet this is no excuſe for the Country, for it is their charge and duty to provide that Robberies be not done, and if they be that they ſuppreſs them; and the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> is made for the maintenance of the peace of the Realm and the advancement of Juſtice,<note place="margin">Cro. Jac. <hi>469.</hi>
                     </note> and therefore ought to be liberally and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably conſtrued, and the perſuing of Felons, who attempt to violate the Sabbath, is no offence but a good work of Charity and Juſtice, for if it were otherwiſe it would prove the occaſion and encouragement of committing Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries frequently upon that day. And ſometimes divers perſons upon neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity are forced to travel upon the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, as Phyſicians, Chirurgeons and Midwives, and it was judged but reaſonable they ſhould be protected in their Journies.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But this Law is in ſome ſort now altered by a Statute made in the 29th: year of the Reign of his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Majeſty, whereby it is provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <q>That if any perſon or perſons whatſoever which ſhall travel upon the Lord's day ſhall be then robbed, That
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:61578:26"/>no Hundred nor the Inhabitants there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhall be charged with it, or be anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for any Robbery ſo committed; but the perſon or perſons ſo robbed ſhall be barred from bringing any Action for the ſaid Robbery, any Law to the contrary notwithſtanding; Nevertheleſs the Inhabitants of the Counties and Hundreds (after notice of any ſuch Robberies to them or ſome of them given, or after Huy and Cry for the ſame to be brought) ſhall make or cauſe to be made freſh ſuit and purſuit after the Offenders with Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and Footmen, according to the Statute made in the 27th. year of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> upon pein of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiting to the King's Majeſty his Heirs and Succeſſors, as much money as might have been recovered againſt the Hundred by the party robbed if this Law had not been made.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:61578:27"/>
               <head>In what place a Robbery muſt be committed to charge the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.</head>
               <p>THE Statute of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> ſpeaks in general as well of the place, as of the time, yet reſolved <hi>Co.</hi> li. 7. in <hi>Sendill</hi>'s Caſe, <q>That if a man be robbed in his Houſe either by day or night, the Hundred in which the Houſe is ſhall not be charged to anſwer for it, and that for three reaſons
<list>
                        <item>1. For that every man's Houſe is his Caſtle, which he is bound to defend at his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril.</item>
                        <item>2. It is not lawfull for another to enter into any man's Houſe for the tuition and ſafeguard of it.</item>
                        <item>3. That ſuch a Robbery for which the Country ſhall anſwer within this Act ought to be done openly, ſo that the Country may take notice of it themſelves.</item>
                     </list>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Though the Law be ſo in caſe of a Robbery committed in a Houſe, yet it ſeems (that ſince this Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute is to be expounded by the rules of the Common Law) that if
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61578:27"/>a Robbery be done in any known place beſides, the Country is liable. It is held in my Lord <hi>Dier</hi>'s Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports,<note place="margin">Dier <hi>210.</hi> Stam. <hi>34.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <q>That if a man be ſlain in the day-time that the Townſhip ſhould be amerced for the eſcape, though the Murther was done in any Fields or Lane belonging to the Town;</q> hence I do infer, that if a perſon be rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in any open or known place out of the High-way, that ſuch Robbery is within the Statute: I conceive this Caſe may ſerve as a rule to expound this Statute by in reference to the place where, as well as that Caſe of the 3<abbr>d.</abbr> of <hi>Ed.</hi> the 3<abbr>d.</abbr> did in point of time, when the Robbery ſhould be committed to charge the Country; for there a Murther was done <hi>veſpere,</hi> in the evening after Sun-ſet, and the place was amerced for the eſcape, and according to the reaſon of this Caſe it was adjudged in the ſeventh Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port in <hi>Aſhpool</hi>'s Caſe, <q>That a Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery done after Sun-ſet and before it was dark was ſufficient to charge the Hundred;</q> So likewiſe becauſe an eſcape in the night is in no caſe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61578:28"/>puniſhable at Common Law, this Statute hath been expounded by the ſame rule that the Country ſhould not anſwer for any Robbery done in the night.</p>
               <p>But there is one Caſe which ſeems to confine all Robberies (which are within the meaning of this Act) to the Common High-way. The Caſe was this, <q>There was a way which was dangerous for Travellers to paſs through, and very chargea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le to be kept in repair, and upon an <hi>ad quod damnum,</hi> it was found accordingly; thereupon the old way was ſtopped up and a new one made through the Fields adjoyning, which was more ſafe and commodious for Paſſengers, and to an Information brought for ſtopping the way this whole matter was pleaded, and Judgment for the King,
<list>
                        <item>1. For that the Owner of the Land through which the new way was made might ſtop it at his pleaſure.</item>
                        <item>2. Becauſe if any Robbery ſhould happen to be committed upon any perſon travelling in this new way, the Country was not liable to make ſatisfaction for it, for that they were not bound to keep Watch
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61578:28"/>and Ward there.</item>
                     </list>
                  </q> 
To this I anſwer, That it is a charge and a duty in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbent upon the Inhabitants of every Country to ſee that no Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries be committed in any place within their reſpective Precincts, and to uſe all means to prevent them, and if they be to ſuppreſs them, and it does not follow that the Country is not anſwerable for any Robbery unleſs the Inhabitants be bound to Watch and Ward at the ſame time and place where and when the Robbery is committed, for then no Robbery done after <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaelmas</hi> and before the Feaſt of the <hi>Aſcention</hi> ſhould bind the Country, nor between the Feaſt of the <hi>Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> unleſs it be done after Sun-ſetting and before Sun-riſing; for by the Statute, no City, Town or Village is obliged to keep Watch but from Sun-ſetting to Sun-riſing, and that at no other time of the year but from the Feaſt of <hi>Aſcention</hi> till <hi>Michaelmas,</hi> neither is it to be thought in reaſon that the number which the Statute does appoint to Watch (<hi>viz.</hi> ſix at every
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:61578:29"/>Gate of a City, twelve to a Tower, and ſix more or leſs according to the proportion of the Inhabitants to every Village) ſhould guard e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular paſſage upon the Road: And Watches are not kept in the night to guard and ſecure Travellers from Robbers in the night, for the Country ſhall not make any ſatisfaction for a Robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry done at that time; but their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs principally is to examine all Strangers (which travel in the night) whence they come, whither they go, and what they be, and of their buſineſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and if they find cauſe of ſuſpicion they may arreſt and detain them till the morning, and if then no ſuſpicion be found they may let them go, and if o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe they ought to deliver them to the Sheriff, or carry them before a Juſtice of the Peace, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And admitting that the Country is bound to keep Watch and Ward in the day-time, according to the 5th. of <hi>Ed.</hi> the 4th. where it was held, <q>That the Inhabitants are not required by Law to Watch and Ward upon the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61578:29"/>Sunday, in the time of Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</q> yet it was reſolved in an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion brought by — againſt the Hundred of <hi>Stokes,</hi> 
                  <q>That not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the Robbery was done upon the Sunday, and in the time of Divine Service that the Plaintiff ſhould recover againſt the Hundred,</q> and I conceive that it may be a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral rule, that in what place ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever a Felony be committed, for which the Town or Hundred were anſwerable at Common Law for the eſcape of any ſuch Felon, that for a Robbery done under the ſame circumſtances the Country ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer. I have onely offered theſe reaſons and ſubmit unto the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Reader.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:61578:30"/>
               <head>How one or more againſt whom Execution is had may have Contribution from the reſt of the Inhabitants of the ſame Hundred.</head>
               <p>BY the Statute of the 13th. of <hi>Ed.</hi> the 1ſt. and 28 of <hi>Ed.</hi> the 3d. the whole Hundred where the Robbery was committed with the Liberties within the Precincts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, being liable to anſwer for the Robbery and the damages ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thereby, when the party rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed had obtained Judgment againſt the Hundred, it was the uſual prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice to take Execution for the intire damage againſt one or very few of the Inhabitants, who being ſo char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged had no remedy to force a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution from the reſidue of the Hundred, which often proved to be the abſolute impoveriſhment and ruine of ſuch Inhabitants and their Families. To remedy this great inconveniency, and to lay the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:61578:30"/>equally upon the Inhabitants of the whole Hundred, who were equally chargeable by a Statute made <hi>Anno</hi> 27 <hi>El.</hi> cap. 13. it is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted,
<q>That after Execution of da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages ſo had by the party againſt one or few of the Inhabitants, it may be lawfull upon complaint made by the perſon or perſons ſo charged, for two Juſtices of the Peace (whereof one to be of the Quorum) of the ſame Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty inhabiting within the ſaid Hundred or near unto the ſame where any ſuch Execution ſhall be had, to aſſeſs and tax ratably and proportionably accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their diſcretions all and every the Towns, Pariſhes, Villages and Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, as well of the ſaid Hundred where any ſuch Robbery ſhall be committed as of the Liberties within the ſaid Hundred to and towards an equal contribution to be had and made for the relief of the ſaid Inhabitant or Inhabitants againſt whom the party or parties robbed had his or their Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And after ſuch taxation made, the Conſtables, Conſtable, Headbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs, or Headborough of every ſuch Town, Pariſh, Village and Hamlet,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:61578:31"/>ſhall by virtue of this Act have full power and authority within their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral limits ratably and proportionably to tax and aſſeſs according to their abilities, every Inhabitant and Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in every ſuch Town, Pariſh, Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage and Hamlet, for and towards the payment of ſuch taxation and aſſeſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as ſhall be ſo made upon every ſuch Town, Pariſh, Village and Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, as aforeſaid by the ſaid Juſtices; And if any Inhabitant of any ſuch Town, Pariſh, Village or Hamlet ſhall obſtinately refuſe and deny to pay the ſaid taxation and aſſeſſment ſo by the ſaid Conſtables, Conſtable, Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boroughs or Headborough taxed and aſſeſſed; Then it ſhall and may be lawfull to and for the ſaid Conſtables Headboroughs, and every of them within their ſeveral limits and juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, to diſtrain all and every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and perſons ſo refuſing or denying by his and their goods and chattels, and the ſame diſtreſs to ſell and the money thereof coming to retain to the uſe aforeſaid; And if the goods and chattels ſo diſtrained and ſold ſhall be of more value than the ſaid taxation
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:61578:31"/>ſhall come to, then the reſidue of the ſaid money over and above the ſaid taxations ſhall be delivered unto the perſon or perſons ſo diſtrained. All and every ſuch Conſtables and Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boroughs after that they have within their ſeveral limits and juriſdictions levied and collected their ſaid rates and ſums of money ſo taxed, ſhall within ten days after ſuch Collection pay and deliver the ſame unto the ſaid Juſtices of Peace or one of them to the uſe and behoof of the ſaid Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitant or Inhabitants for whom ſuch rate, taxation or aſſeſſment ſhall be had or made as aforeſaid, which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney ſo payed ſhall by the Juſtices or Juſtice ſo receiving the ſame be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered over (upon requeſt made) unto the ſaid Inhabitant or Inhabitants to whoſe uſe the ſame ſhall be called.</q>
               </p>
               <p>It was held in one <hi>Dean</hi>'s Caſe 10 <hi>Car.</hi> in the Common Pleas,
<q>That a perſon coming to inhabit in the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred after the Robbery, and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment given, is not liable to the Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at the Suit of the party robbed, but a perſon coming after to inhabit is aſſeſſable to the Contribution, becauſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:61578:32"/>the Country is chargeable at the time of the aſſeſſment and not the perſons which were there at the time of the Robbery committed. </q>
Vid. <hi>Dalton's</hi> Juſtic. 153.</p>
               <p>There was another inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency (before the making of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Statute of 27 <hi>El.</hi>) which occaſioned great remiſſneſs and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligence in the purſuing and appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending of Robbers, for that by the Statutes of 13 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. and 28 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. the Hundred where the Robbery was done ſtood charged with the penalties therein contained, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their diſability to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form what the Law required from them, and likewiſe notwithſtanding they uſed their uttermoſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours in making of freſh ſuit and following the Malefactors in order to bring them to juſtice; the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of other Hundreds and Counties (beſides thoſe where the Robbery was done) knowing that though the Felons eſcaped that they were not bound to render ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to the party robbed, were careleſs in diſcharging their duty in proſecuting the Huy and Cry
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:61578:32"/>when it was brought to them; And to the end that the Inhabitants and Reſiants of other places might be quickened and ſpurred on to uſe all poſſible diligence to ſuppreſs Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, the aforeſaid Statute of 27 <hi>El.</hi> makes them who ſhall firſt make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault in the purſuit to participate of the charge, which before was incumbent onely upon that place where the party was robbed, It is thereby enacted,
<q>That the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of every or any ſuch Hundred (with the Liberties within the precinct thereof) wherein negligence, fault, or defect of purſuit after Huy and Cry made, ſhall happen to be, ſhall anſwer and ſatisfie the one moiety or half of all and every ſum or ſums of money and damages as ſhall by force and virtue of the ſaid Statutes of <hi>13 Ed. 1.</hi> and <hi>28 Ed. 3.</hi> or either of them be recovered or had againſt, or of the ſame Hundred with the Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes therein in which any Robbery or Felony ſhall at any time hereafter be committed or done, And the ſame moiety ſhall at any time hereafter be recovered by Action of Debt, Bill,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:61578:33"/>Plaint or Information in any of the King's Courts of Record at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> by and in the name of the Clerk of the Peace for the time being of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſuch County within this Realm where any ſuch Robbery and Recovery by the party or parties robbed ſhall be without naming the Chriſtian-name or Sir-name of the ſaid Clerk of the Peace, which moiety ſo recovered ſhall be to the onely uſe and behoof of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the ſaid Hundred where any ſuch Robbery ſhall be committed.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And leſt the Action, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſhould any way miſcarry, either by the death or removal of the Clerk of the Peace it is further provided by the ſaid Act,
<q>
                     <p>That if any Clerk of the Peace of or in any County within this Realm ſhall at any time hereafter commence or prefer any ſuch Suit, Action or Information, and ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the ſame ſo ſued, commenced or preferred happen to die or to be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved out of his Office before Recovery and Execution had, yet no ſuch Action, Bill, Plaint, Suit or Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation ſued, commenced or preferred, ſhall by ſuch diſplacing or death, be
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:61578:33"/>abated, diſcontinued or ended, But it ſhall and may be lawfull to and for the Clerk of the Peace next ſucceeding in the ſaid County to proſecute, purſue and follow all and every ſuch Action, Bill, Plaint, Suit or Information for the cauſes aforeſaid ſo hanging and depending in ſuch manner and form to all intents and purpoſes as that Clerk of the Peace might have done which firſt commenced or preferred the ſaid Suit, Bill, Plaint or Information.</p>
                     <p>If the moiety of the penalty be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered in an Action brought upon the foreſaid branch of this Statute againſt any Hundred for want of freſh ſuit and Execution had there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon againſt one or few of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants; There ſhall be the ſame courſe and method obſerved as is provided by this Statute for relief of part of the Inhabitants (of that place where the Robbery was done) whoſe goods and chattels are taken in Execution for the ſatisfaction of the perſon that is rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, And the like taxation, aſſeſſment, levying by diſtreſs and payment ſhall be had and done within every Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred where default and negligence of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:61578:34"/>purſuit and freſh ſuit ſhall be, for and to the benefit of all and every Inhabitant or Inhabitants of the ſame Hundred where ſuch default ſhall be, that ſhall at any time hereafter by virtue of this Act have any damages or money levyed of them for the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the one moiety of the money recovered againſt the ſaid Hundred where the Robbery is committed.</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>There is a private Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment made in the 39 <hi>El.</hi> cap. 25. for the relief of the Inhabitants of <hi>Begnerſh</hi> alias <hi>Benherſt</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Berkſhire,</hi> who in reſpect of the ſmalneſs and poverty of the place were not able to make ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for the great and frequent Robberies committed within that Hundred, which hath two great Roads in it, the one leading from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Henly</hi> upon <hi>Thames,</hi> the other from <hi>London</hi> to <hi>Reading,</hi> each of them being at leaſt three miles in length thorough the woody ground called the <hi>Thicket;</hi> And in reſpect of the thinneſs of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, and few or none of their Villages being ſituated upon either
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:61578:34"/>of theſe Roads; And having ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom any occaſion for themſelves or their Servants to be much conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant in or near the Roads, moſt part of the Hundred joyning to the High-way being woody ground, and ſo not fit for Tillage or Paſture, or any other uſe which may require the frequent being of the Reſiants upon it. And ſo for theſe reaſons they could not conveniently of themſelves take notice of the Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries committed upon theſe Roads. And therefore to eaſe them of the inconveniencies and of the great charges that they were equally like to undergo, to their utter impoveriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and depopulation, it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided by this Act,
<q>That the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the ſaid Hundred of <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſt</hi> ſhall and may to their own proper uſe in the name of the Clerk of the Peace of the ſaid County recover and leavy all ſuch ſums of money, coſts and damages as ſhall hereafter be recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red or levied of or againſt them by force of any of the Statutes which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern Robberies, againſt the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants and Reſiants of every or any ſuch
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:61578:35"/>Hundred with the Franchiſes within the precincts thereof, wherein negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, fault or defect of ſuch purſuit or freſh ſuit (as by the ſaid Statute of <hi>27 El.</hi> is appointed to be made) ſhall happen to be after notice given or Hay and Cry brought to the ſaid Inhabitants or Reſiants or any of them of or upon any Robbery which ſhall be committed within the Hundred of <hi>Benherſt:</hi> And this Act ſhall give full power and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in all reſpects to the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the ſaid Hundred of <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herſt</hi> (in the name of the Clerk of the Peace of the ſaid County) for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery and levying of all the ſaid mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, coſts and damages aforeſaid, as the Statute of <hi>27 El.</hi> gave or intends to give for the recovery of a moiety or one half thereof. Provided always that no ſuch remedy or recovery ſhall be had by this Statute for all or the whole ſum or ſums of money and da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages aforeſaid, but onely in theſe two caſes (viz.) The one where no ſuch notice or intelligence (as by the ſaid Statute of the <hi>27 El.</hi> was appointed to be given of every or any Robbery) ſhall be given to the Inhabitants of the ſaid
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:61578:35"/>Hundred of <hi>Benherſt;</hi> The other where the Inhabitants of the ſame Hundred (after ſuch notice of any Robbery to them or ſome of them given, or after Hay and Cry for the ſame to them brought) ſhall make or cauſe to be made freſh ſuit and purſuit after the Offenders with Horſemen and Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, according to the ſaid Statute of <hi>27 El.</hi> and where nevertheleſs the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders or any one of them ſhall not be apprehended within forty days af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Robbery committed.</q>
               </p>
               <p>One of the chief difficulties that the ſaid Hundred of <hi>Benherſt</hi> labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red under was in regard the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants thereof for the reaſons alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhewed could not of themſelves take notice of the Robbery that they might make freſh ſuit after the Offenders, and nothing could ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them of the penalty unleſs they or ſome other place anſwer the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of all or any of the Robbers, and the party robbed was not obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to give notice within the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred wherein he was robbed, for notice in another Hundred or Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is ſufficient, provided it be near
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:61578:36"/>the place where the Robbery was done, as it appears by the preamble of this Statute of 39 <hi>El.</hi> 
                  <q>That upon a notice given at <hi>Maidenhead</hi> out of the Hundred of <hi>Benherſt,</hi> and three miles diſtant from thoſe thieviſh pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Thicket where the Robbery was committed, recovery and Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion were had againſt the ſaid Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred for above two Hundred and fifty pounds;</q>
and you may reade in the Chapter of Notice before, how no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice given at <hi>South-Mims</hi> in <hi>Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſex</hi> of a Robbery done in <hi>Hertford-ſhire</hi> was adjudged good. And not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this Act, if a Travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler be robbed within the Hundred of <hi>Benherſt,</hi> and gives notice of the Robbery at another place out of the Hundred as aforeſaid, yet the ſaid Hundred ſhall anſwer for the Robbery as formerly, for the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Statute is not, that if there be notice at all give to the Inhabitants of the ſaid Hundred, that for that reaſon they ſhall be excuſed of the penalty, but that if there be no ſuch notice given to them within the Hundred, and the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:61578:36"/>party robbed recover againſt them, they ſhall recover over againſt the place where default of freſh ſuit ſhall happen the whole and intire penalty recovered againſt them. And in caſe there be ſuch notice and intelligence given to the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants or Reſiants of this Hundred as the Statute does require, and the Offenders eſcape, yet they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the moiety according to the Statute of the 27 <hi>El.</hi> againſt the Hundred where the freſh ſuit cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is another private Act made for the relief of the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of the Town of <hi>Tewxbury,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">8 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 27.</note> in the County of <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> againſt the Commonalty of the <hi>Foreſt Dean,</hi> and of the Hundreds of <hi>Bledſtow</hi> and <hi>Weſtbury,</hi> in the ſaid County, for that Sundry Robberies were u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually committed in a riotous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner by a great multitude of people of the ſaid Commonalty upon the ſaid Inhabitants of the Town of <hi>Tewxbury</hi> in their paſſage from thence upon the River of <hi>Severn</hi> to the City of <hi>Briſtol</hi> and in their
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:61578:37"/>return back again, therefore to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy theſe great enormities,
<q>
                     <p>The Sheriff of the ſaid County or the Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liffs of the Town of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> for the time being or one of them, upon pein of forfeiture of <hi>20li.</hi> to be levied of their lands, goods and chattels to the King's uſe, ſhall make proclamation at the ſaid Town of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> within four days next after notification made to them or any of them by the perſons ſo endamaged, or by any other in their names of ſuch injuries and treſpaſſes done, and that the ſaid Treſpaſſers and Offenders ſhall reſtore in the ſame Town of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> within fifteen days after the ſaid proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the ſaid perſons ſo endamaged their corn and merchandiſe, goods and chattels ſo taken or the very value of the ſame, with reaſonable amends for the damages ſuſtained by ſuch taking; After which proclamation if the ſaid Treſpaſſers do not reſtore the ſaid corn and merchandiſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or the value of them to the party ſo grieved in form aforeſaid, with reaſonable amends for the damages, or that the ſaid Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſers be not brought to the King's
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:61578:37"/>Priſon to the Caſtle of <hi>Gloceſter</hi> for the ſaid treſpaſſes, by the Officers of the ſaid Foreſt and Hundreds, or by the Commonalties of the ſame, that then the conſideration of the Statute of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> put for the Robbery of any perſon which giveth an Action for him that is robbed againſt the Hundred within which the ſame Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery is done, after the form of the ſame Statute, the ſaid Commonalties ſhall be charged of the ſaid corn and merchandiſe, goods and chattels ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or of the very value of the ſame to the party ſo grieved, to ſatisfie them of the damages for the ſame ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king. And that the ſaid parties ſo endamaged and grieved may have their general Actions of Debt againſt the ſaid Commonalties of the ſaid Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and Hundreds of the ſum of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, to which the value of the corn, merchandiſes, goods and chattels ſo taken do extend.</p>
                     <p>And although the ſaid Commonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties be no Commonalties Corporate, yet they ſhall have proceſs in ſuch Actions of Debt by Summons, Attachments and Diſtreſs, as if he were to have
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:61578:38"/>an Action of Debt at the Common Law; So that if the ſaid Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monalties make default of the ſecond diſtreſs in ſuch Actions, that then the party which ſhall ſue ſhall have Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to recover his Debt againſt the ſaid Commonalties, after the ſuppoſal of their goods in the form aforeſaid, with his reaſonable damages and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences; And whatſoever iſſue triable by Inqueſt in the ſaid Foreſt and Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds, ſhall happen to be taken in ſuch Actions, it ſhall be tried by Inqueſt of the Body of the ſaid County out of the ſame Foreſt and Hundreds; And that the goods and chattels of every ſingular perſon of the ſaid Commonal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties for the time being ſhall be had, taken and holden in Law convict, as the common goods and chattels of the ſaid Commonalties touching the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, ſerving and execution of Writs, Proceſſes and Judgments in and of the ſaid Actions. And that every ſingular perſon of the ſaid Foreſt and Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties have power by authority of the ſaid Parliament to attach and arreſt the ſaid Treſpaſſers by their Bodies, as well within the ſaid Foreſt as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:61578:38"/>and ſo arreſted to commit to the ſaid Priſon, and that the Keeper of the ſame Priſon upon pein of <hi>40 <abbr>li.</abbr>
                        </hi> to be levied of his goods and chattels, lands and tenements to the King's uſe, ſhall ſafely keep every ſuch perſon ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his cuſtody till that the King or his Council hath ordained and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided their deliverance upon record, and if the goods or chattels of any ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular perſon or perſons of the ſaid Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt and Hundreds, being not guilty of the ſaid Robberies happen to be put in Execution by reaſon of any ſuch Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Judgment, that then the ſaid perſon and perſons ſo being not guilty may have their ſpecial Action of Debt or Treſpaſs upon the caſe, of the goods and chattels ſo upon Execution againſt the ſaid Treſpaſſers, to recover their damages as well for the value of the ſame goods and chattels ſo put in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, as for the damages and coſts which happen to be had by reaſon of ſuch Actions of Debt, and they ſhall have ſuch Proceſſes in the ſaid Actions of Debt or Treſpaſs as is to be had in the ſaid Actions of Debt for the ſaid perſons ſo endamaged or ſpoiled.</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:61578:39"/>
               <head>Of Huy and Cry.</head>
               <p>FElony is ſo odious in the eye of Law that it puniſheth the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour thereof with death, and will in no manner connive at the impunity ſuch heinous Malefactors, and leſt ſuch violators of the peace ſhould eſcape her Juſtice, ſhe commands and requires the aid and aſſiſtance of all perſons to apprehend and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the Offender, and in caſe he be not taken in the Fact, to give by degrees a general and univerſal Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arm throughout the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for all people to take notice of the Offender; ſo that they may purſue and follow him in order to prevent his flight. And this grand Alarm is called in Law <hi>A Huy and Cry.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Huer</hi> in French (from whence the Law-Latin word <hi>Huteſium</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived) ſignifies to hoot or ſhout, in Engliſh to Cry; And the two words Huy and Cry have but one ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:61578:39"/>and as my Lord <hi>Cook</hi> terms it, the one is but an expreſſion of the other, and ſometimes one is uſed without the other, as in <hi>Weſtm.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. where all men are comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be ready at the Cry of the Country. And the Law does not require that this Huy and Cry be made onely with a vocal ſound, but it may well anſwer the ends of the Law if it be performed by an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as a Horn, a Trumpet, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as the <hi>Mirour</hi> and <hi>Briton</hi> have it, <hi>avec Huy &amp; Cry de Corne &amp; de Bouche,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 173.</note> 
                  <hi>(viz.)</hi> with Huy and Cry of Horn and Mouth.</p>
               <p>This way of purſuing Felons by Huy and Cry is part of the ancient Common Law of this Realm, as it appears by thoſe Authours who write of the Laws of <hi>England</hi> in uſe long before the Conqueſt, yet ſome have thought that Huy and Cry had its original from the foreſaid Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of <hi>Weſtm.</hi> 1. but that Statute it ſelf proves the contrary, for it finds fault that good ſuit, that is freſh ſuit was not duly made.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:61578:40"/>
               <head>Who may raiſe the Huy and Cry, and for what Cauſe.</head>
               <p>THere are two ſorts of Huy and Cry, The one by Common Law, the other by Statute. The Huy and Cry by Common Law may be levied by any perſon who finds juſt cauſe to doe it; neither when a Felony is committed is it neceſſary for him to reſort to the Conſtable of the Town where it was done, and acquaint him with the cauſe, deſcribing the perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire him to begin it, but that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the party grieved or one that is eye Witneſs to the fact may raiſe the Huy and Cry themſelves, and the people of the Town are bound to follow it when it is once ſo raiſed, and if the party does not ſo he incurs the penalty of the Law. For if a man be preſent when one is either robbed or murthered,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3</hi> Inſt. <hi>117. 8</hi> Ed. <hi>2.</hi> Coron. <hi>395.</hi>
                  </note> and does not endeavour to arreſt the Offender, he is puniſhable by Fine
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:61578:40"/>and impriſonment; And ſo was the Law of old, <hi>Siquis aliquem ſpoliatum viderit, ſontem per acela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mationem inſequatur,</hi> and it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to be found amongſt the Laws of <hi>Carnutus</hi> that if a man met a Robber in the way,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 116.</note> and would ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer him to paſs without raiſing the Huy and Cry upon him, he was to pay the uttermoſt penny the Felons life ſhould be valued at.</p>
               <p>It is not neceſſary that the Huy and Cry be made by the Conſtable, the party grieved, or him that ſaw the fact committed, nor that it be raiſed in the Town where the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony was done, but that in all ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes where every man has authority by a warrant in Law to arreſt an Offender, as a man attainted or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted of Treaſon or Felony, may be apprehended by any perſon whatſoever, if an attempt be made to arreſt any ſuch perſon and he diſobeys it and flies, the Huy and Cry may be levied upon him where ever he be.</p>
               <p>If a Felony be done, and <hi>A.</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects <hi>John a-Styles</hi> to be the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:61578:41"/>that committed it, the ſuſpici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on being perſonal none can attach him beſides <hi>A.</hi> in this caſe if <hi>A.</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to apprehend him and he makes his eſcape,<note place="margin">2 <hi>H.</hi> 7. ſo. 15.</note> I conceive <hi>A.</hi> may raiſe the Cry after him becauſe he had power to arreſt him.</p>
               <p>Note the Spectators are not to be Judges of the degree or quality of the offence; for it one kills ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by chance-medly or <hi>ſe defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendo</hi> and flies for it, the Town ſhall be amerced for the eſcape, and by the ſame reaſon they may raiſe the Huy and Cry upon him, becauſe the Inhabitants being bound to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend him, the Law allows them the means to effect it, and one of them is by Huy and Cry.</p>
               <p>Every Juſtice of the Peace by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his Commiſſion may cauſe Huy and Cry,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dal. J. P.</hi> cap. 28.</note> freſh ſuit and ſearch to be made upon any Murther, Robbery or Theft committed.</p>
               <p>The Statute of the 3<abbr>d.</abbr> of <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. entitled <hi>Officium Coronatoris,</hi> does ordain, <q>That upon all Homicides, Burglaries, men ſlain or put in great danger, the Huy and Cry ſhall be le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied;</q>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:61578:41"/>though generally a Felony ought to be the ground and foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Huy and Cry, yet in ſome caſes it may be done though there be no Felony,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Inſt.</hi> ib. ſupra.</note> as if a man be dangerouſly wounded or aſſaulted and attempted to be robbed, in both theſe caſes, though in the one there was but a probability of a Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony, and in the other onely a will (diſcovered by the attempt) to commit it; So it ſeems if a rape be attempted upon a woman, ſhe may juſtifie the levying of the Huy and Cry though ſhe was not raviſhed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed.</p>
               <p>The Huy and Cry is appointed to be raiſed in ſome particular ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes by Acts of Parliament, as the Statute of <hi>Wincheſter</hi> doth authoriſe the Watch to arreſt night walkers, and if they diſobey the arreſt and fly, the Watchmen may make Huy and Cry,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Stat.</hi> Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton <hi>cap.</hi> 3. 4 <hi>H.</hi> 7. ſo. 2.18.</note> and ſuch perſon ſhall be purſued from Town to Town and from Country to Country in the ſame manner with the Felon.</p>
               <p>It is likewiſe ordained by a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute made <hi>An.</hi> 21 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <q>That if a
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:61578:42"/>Foreſter, Parker or Warrener, ſhall find any Malefactors wandring within their reſpective precincts, with an intent to commit any treſpaſs or damage there,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 117.</note> the ſaid Officers may levy the Huy and Cry upon them; and if the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders thereupon will not render them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the ſaid Officers, but fly or make reſiſtance, if any of them be ſlain by the forementioned Officers, or by any other coming to their aſſiſtance, within their bounds or limits, and for the killing of ſuch Offenders no perſon ſhall be anſwerable to the Law.</q>
               </p>
               <p>As the Law gives authority to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man to raiſe the Country when there is a juſt and legal cauſe for it; ſo it does inflict a puniſhment upon ſuch as ſhall alarm their Country without ſufficient grounds to doe it; for if any man ſhall upon a feigned cauſe raiſe a Huy and Cry upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 118. 29 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Fitz Treſp.</hi> 252.</note> he may be puniſhed by Fine and impriſonment, and likewiſe may be bound to his good beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour as a diſturber of the publick peace.</p>
               <p>And to the end that Malefactors ſhould find no ſhelter or protection
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:61578:42"/>under the wings of any great Men or chief Officers of any Country, and to engage them as well as other Inhabitants to promote the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Cry, it is ordained by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of <hi>Weſtm.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 9. 
<q>That if de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault be found in the Lord of a Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe the King ſhall ſeiſe the Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe into his own hands, and if de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault be found in his Bailiff he ſhall ſuffer one years impriſonment and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards make Fine to the King, and if he hath not wherewith, he ſhall be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned for two years; And if the Sheriff, Coroner, or any Bailiff with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſuch Franchiſe or without, for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, or intreaty, or any affinity con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal, conſent or procure to conceal the Felonies done within their Liberties, or otherwiſe will not attach or arreſt ſuch Felons (whereas they may) or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe will not doe their Offices for fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that they bear to ſuch Offenders, and be thereof convicted, they ſhall be impriſoned for one year, and if they have not whereof to make Fine, they ſhall have three years impriſonment.</q>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 173</note>My Lord <hi>Cook</hi> in his Comment upon this Statute ſays that the King
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:61578:43"/>for ſuch default ſhall retain the Franchiſe to himſelf for ever as forfeited;And <hi>Anno</hi> 30 <hi>H.</hi> 3. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the making of this Statute, <hi>W. de Haverhull,</hi> the Kings Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer, was commanded to ſeiſe the City of <hi>London</hi> into the King's hand, for that the Citizens thereof did not levy Huy and Cry for the death of Mr. <hi>Guido de Arterio</hi> and others ſlain there,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 118.</note> as the Laws and Cuſtoms of the Realm did require.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>How and in what manner the freſh ſuit and purſuit is to be made upon a Huy and Cry le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied.</head>
               <p>THE Statutes of the 13 of <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. 28 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 11. do command in general that Huy and Cry be made after Felons from Town to Town and from Country to Country; But it ſeems that at Common Law the method of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:61578:43"/>Felons was, That the party robbed or otherwiſe grieved, or ſome perſon for him (though that be not neceſſary as I have ſhewed before) ſhould repair to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable of the Town, and give him notice of the Felony, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire him to raiſe the Huy and Cry, and the Conſtable ought to raiſe the power of the Town, and if the Offender be not found there to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on the Huy and Cry to the next Conſtable, who was to doe the like in his Town, and ſo from Conſtable to Conſtable untill the Offender be taken, and this is to be done as well in the night as by day. <hi>Cook</hi> 3 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 116. 2 <hi>Ed.</hi> 4.8, 9.</p>
               <p>It ſeems no Town is bound to purſue any further than to the next Conſtable,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Co.</hi> li. 7. ſo. 7. <hi>Dier</hi> 370.</note> for ſuch a purſuit is a good excuſe for them if the Town be endicted at the King's Suit for the eſcape of a Felon. And every Town in this reſpect is a diſtinct Body, and ought to aid and aſſiſt their Conſtable (when he requires them) in the execution of his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; as the whole County is bound
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:61578:44"/>to obey the Sheriff's command when he hath occaſion to make uſe of the <hi>Poſſe Comitatus;</hi> And if the Inhabitants of any Town were obliged to proſecute a Felon fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than to the next Conſtable, then by the ſame reaſon they might be required to go on from one end of the Kingdom to the other, which is both inconvenient and unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</p>
               <p>And this ſeems to be the Law be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Conqueſt,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mirour</hi> cap. 1.</note> for the <hi>Mirour of Juſtice,</hi> treating of the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the ancient. Kings, ſaith, it was Ordained, 
<q>That every one of the age of fourteen years and upwards ſhould follow criminal Offenders from Village to Village at the Huy and Cry;</q>
it is ſaid elſewhere that 
<q>Pervetuſta Anglorum Lege ſancitum eſt ut ſiquis damnum ex Furto paſſus,<note place="margin">3 <hi>Inſt.</hi> 172.</note> aut qui ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum ſpoliatum viderit ſontem per ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamationem inſequatur, Conſtabulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us ejus Villa cujus opem implorat, auxilia ciere, furemque perquirexe debet, quod ſi furem illic non depren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derit in proximam tranſmigrare, &amp; Conſtabulariam ad ferendas ſuppetias
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:61578:44"/>iterum invocare,</q>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">It is eſtabliſhed by the ancient Law of <hi>England,</hi> that if any perſon be robbed, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he himſelf or one that ſees the Robbery done, may follow the Offender with a Huy and Cry, and the Conſtable of that Village whoſe help he requires, ought to call in aid and make enquiry after the Felon, and if he cannot find him there he ought to repair to the next Village and require the Conſtable of that place to bring in further aid to purſue the Felon.</q>
               </p>
               <p>If a Huy and Cry be levied, the Officer of the Town where the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lony, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is done, as alſo the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of other Towns whither the Huy and Cry is brought ought to give notice to all the Towns round about them reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, and not to one next Town onely,<note place="margin">Dal. J. P. <hi>cap. 28.</hi>
                  </note> to the end that the Cry may ſpread it ſelf far and wide into all Countries; So that it may be in a manner impoſſible for the Felon to eſcape, and in ſuch caſes it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to give notice in writing
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:61578:45"/>(to the purſuers) of the things ſtoln, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and of the colours and marks thereof, and likewiſe to give a deſcription of the perſon of the Felon, his Horſe and Apparel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and (if it can be known) to ſhew which way he is gone.</p>
               <p>After notice given,<note place="margin">St. 3 <hi>Fd.</hi> 1. de <hi>Offic.</hi> Cor. <hi>Braclon</hi> li. 3.10.121.</note> the purſuit from place to place muſt be made immediately, with all the haſte and expedition that may be, and that likewiſe carefully and induſtriouſly, and the purſuers if poſſible are to find out the Felon's footſteps, and to tract him all the way he went, and to uſe all other devices and means which may ſeem moſt condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing and effectual for the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Felon, ſince our Law of <hi>England</hi> directs the purſuers to tract the Felon, I cannot paſs over in ſilence what the learned Sir <hi>John Davice</hi> mentions in his Preface to his <hi>Reports,</hi>
                  <q>That amongſt the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold abſurdities of the <hi>Brehon</hi>'s Laws, formerly in uſe amongſt the Iriſh, they had one cuſtom that deſerves imitation, which was, That if any cattel were ſtoln and the Owner followed the tract</q>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:61578:45"/>(wherein, ſaith the Authour, the Iriſh are incredible cunning, inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as they can find the ſame by the bruiſing of a graſs in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer-time) 
<q>if the perſon into whoſe land the tract is brought cannot make it off into ſome other land, he is to anſwer the ſtealth to the Owner; and this Law is ratified there as both uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and neceſſary for that Kingdom, though the reſt of the <hi>Brehon</hi>'s Laws be aboliſhed.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Sir <hi>Nicholas Hide</hi> delivered in his Charge at <hi>Cambridge</hi> Aſſiſes, <hi>Anno</hi> 1629.<note place="margin">Dal. J. P. <hi>cap. 28.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <q>That a Huy and Cry muſt be made and purſued with Horſemen and Footmen, and that not onely a private ſearch muſt be made in every Town, but that they muſt raiſe the Country as they go, and all ſtill to follow the Huy and Cry as againſt a common Enemy.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo if a Huy and Cry be brought into a Town the Officers thereof ought forthwith to ſearch all ſuſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Houſes and places within their limits; And any perſon who fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows the Huy and Cry (whether he be an Officer or no) may arreſt all
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:61578:46"/>ſuch perſons as in the ſearch or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuit ſhall be found ſuſpicious, and thereupon he that is ſo ſuſpected ought to be carried before ſome Juſtice of the Peace of the Country where he is taken to be examined where he was at the time of the Felony committed.</p>
               <p>It is provided by the Statute of the 27 <hi>El.</hi>
                  <q>That no Huy and Cry made by the Country or Inhabitants of any Hundred ſhall be allowed for a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Huy and Cry or purſuit unleſs the ſame be done both with Horſemen and Footmen,</q>
                  <hi>Quere,</hi> Whether this Statute extends to a purſuit at Common Law or at the ſuit of the King,<note place="margin">27 <hi>Eliz.</hi> cap. 13.</note> or onely to a purſuit to be made at the ſuit of the party rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, who is to recover againſt the Hundred upon the Statute of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:61578:46"/>
               <head>Who are bound to purſue upon the Huy and Cry levied.</head>
               <p>WHen the Huy and Cry is rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed every Inhabitant (whoſe aſſiſtance the Law requires) ought to follow it, though he receives no command or notice thereof from any Officer who hath authority to demand their aid in this caſe, for if a Felony, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be committed and a Villor hears the Huy and Cry thereupon levied, he is not to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect command or notice from any perſon, but ought immediately to follow the Cry; for the Law which enjoins this duty upon him gives him a tacit command to doe it, and the Huy and Cry it ſelf (being once heard) is a ſufficient notice; And this Law is as ancient as we are able to trace it by the light of Letters; for many years before the Conqueſt it was held for Law,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Canuti</hi> Leges.</note> that if any man heard the Huy and Cry and did not purſue, he was to be
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:61578:47"/>puniſhed as a Contemner of the King's Laws.</p>
               <p>The Statute of <hi>Weſtm.</hi> 1. being but in affirmance of the Common Law commands <q>all perſons to be in readineſs to arreſt Felons when ever the Cry of the Country ſummons their attendance,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Weſt.</hi> 1. cap. 3.</note>
                  </q> and by another Statute made the next year after it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, <q>That all perſons ſhall follow the Huy and Cry, and whoever does not and be thereof convicted ſhall be attached to anſwer before the Juſtices of Gaol delivery, and for ſuch offence ſhall be fined and impriſoned.<note place="margin">Offic. Cor. <hi>4</hi> Ed. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </q> Brac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton <hi>li.</hi> 3. <hi>fo.</hi> 118. 3 <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Coron<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 333.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Bracton,</hi> who writ before any Statute made concerning Huy and Cry, ſaith, <q>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bracton</hi> li. 3. fo. 118.</note>That all Knights and others under the age of fifteen years, ought to take an Oath that they will not receive any outlawed perſons, Murtherers, Robbers, or ſuch as have committed Burglary, and if at any time they ſhould hear the Huy and Cry raiſed they ſhould immediately follow it with their whole Family,</q> and herewith agrees <hi>Briton</hi> fo. 15, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>9
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:61578:47"/>but <hi>The Mirour of Juſtice,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mirour</hi> cap. 1.</note> who was the firſt Authour that writ of the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> relates it to be a Law eſtabliſhed by the ancient Kings of this Realm, <q>That ſuch as be but of fourteen years of age are bound to purſue Felons upon the Huy and Cry.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding what is ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be general, and its literal ſenſe comprehends all perſons, yet there are ſome that may claim an exemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from this ſervice or duty; As, if a man be ſick and not able to travel, the Law will allow him a privilege in reſpect of his infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as well in this as in other caſes; for if a <hi>Pracipe quod Reddat</hi> be brought againſt <hi>John a-Stiles</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnable at ſuch a day, the Tenant may be eſſoined <hi>de mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lecto,</hi> that is, he may be excuſed of his appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and thereby prevent his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault, becauſe he is ſick a bed and cannot travel; So if the Sheriff ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts a man that is ſick and returns <hi>Languidus,</hi> this is a good return, and the Sheriff ſhall not be amer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, for the Law conſtrains no man
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:61578:48"/>to expoſe his life to imminent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, unleſs it be in the defence of the Commonweale, wherein the publick ſafety ought to be dearer to every man than his life.</p>
               <p>A man may be exempted in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of any other corporal infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, whereby he is viſibly diſabled to effect that which the Law ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects to be done, for <hi>Lex non cogit ad impoſſibilia.</hi> The purſuit ought to be made by men that are endued with ſtrength and agility of Body, ſo that the purſuer may be in a ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to follow the Felon, either by running or riding, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual ſpeed to that of the Malefac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, whoſe fear and the ſenſe of his guilt adds vigour to his flight, and puts him upon all deſperate enterpriſes in this extremity, and to oblige a blind or lame perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the performance of this Office were to no end, but ſhould be in it ſelf <hi>vanus &amp; inutilis labor,</hi> and from the ſame reaſon I infer that one over-grown with years may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed in reſpect of his age, as a perſon <hi>ſuperannuated</hi> is freed from
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:61578:48"/>ſerving upon Juries. As for age, I conceive there is no certain term of years limited when any perſon ſhall either begin or ceaſe to purſue upon the Huy and Cry, but in this caſe the abilities of the body muſt be the ſtanding rule, as that of the mind in committing of Felonies; for though the Law computes four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years to be the age of diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet if one under that age kills another, and it can be diſcovered by any circumſtance that he had underſtanding, to diſcern betwixt good and the evil he had done, the Law will adjudge it Murther, for in this caſe <hi>malitia ſupplet atatem;</hi> ſo that if a perſon of younger years be of greater ſtrength and ability of body than one of twice his years, who is weak and infirm and not able to anſwer the end of the Law, ſuch perſon may be required to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue an Offender upon the Huy and Cry, (notwithſtanding the two a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid authorities) for his capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city of performing the duty, brings him within the reaſon of the Law, which being altered alters the Law
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:61578:49"/>it ſelf, for <hi>ratio Legis eſt anima Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis &amp; mutata Legis ratione mutatur &amp; Lex.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="statutory_law">
               <div rend="margQuotes" type="statute">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Statute of</hi> Weſtm. 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. Anno 3 E. 1.</head>
                  <head>Of Robberies.</head>
                  <p>FOraſmuch as the peace of this Realm hath been weakly kept heretofore, for lack of quick and freſh ſuit making after Felons in due manner,<note place="margin">Freſh ſuit.</note> and namely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of Franchiſes, where the Felons are received: It is provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that all generally be ready and apparelled at the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and ſummons of Sheriffs,<note place="margin">Sheriffs.</note> and at the Cry of the Country, to purſue and arreſt Felons,<note place="margin">Arreſt.</note> when any need is, as well within Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſes as without;<note place="margin">Franchiſes.</note> and they that
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:61578:49"/>will not ſo doe,<note place="margin">Refuſe.</note> and thereof be attainted, ſhall make a grievous Fine to the King. And if default be found in the Lord of the Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe,<note place="margin">Fine.</note> the King ſhall take him to the ſame Franchiſe:<note place="margin">Franchiſes.</note> and if de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault be in the Bailiff,<note place="margin">Bailiff.</note> he ſhall have one years impriſonment,<note place="margin">Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> and after ſhall make a grievous Fine,<note place="margin">Fine.</note> and if he have not where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, he ſhall have impriſonment of two years: and if the Sheriff,<note place="margin">Sheriff.</note> Coroner,<note place="margin">Coroner.</note> or other Bailiff within Franchiſe or without, for Reward or for Prayer, or for any manner of affinity, conceal,<note place="margin">Conceal.</note> conſent or procure to conceal the Felonies done in their Bailiwicks,<note place="margin">Attach.</note> 
                     <note place="margin">Office.</note> or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe do forbear to attach or arreſt ſuch Felons (there as they may) or otherwiſe to doe their Office for favour born to ſuch miſdoers,<note place="margin">Favour.</note> and be attainted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, they ſhall have one years im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment,<note place="margin">Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> and after make a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous Fine;<note place="margin">Fine.</note> and if they have not whereof to make Fine, they ſhall have impriſonment of three years. <hi>Weſtm.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>Anno</hi> 3 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1.
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:61578:50"/>and after <hi>Anno</hi> 23 <hi>H.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. it is enacted that this Statute ſhall be put in execution.</p>
               </div>
               <div rend="margQuotes" type="statute">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Statute of</hi> Winton, Anno 13 Ed. 1.</head>
                  <head>Of Robberies.</head>
                  <p>FOraſmuch as from day to day Robberies, Murthers and burning of Houſes be more often uſed than they have been hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and Felons cannot be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainted by the Oath of Jurors, which had rather ſuffer Felonies done to ſtrangers to paſs without pein, than to indict the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, of whom a great part be folk of the ſame Country, or at the leaſt, if the Offenders be of another Country, the Receivers be of places near; and they doe
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:61578:50"/>the ſame, becauſe the Oath is not now put unto Jurors, nor upon the Country where ſuch Felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies were done, as to the reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of damages hitherto no pein hath been limited for their concealment and laches: Our Lord the King, for to abate the power of Felons, hath eſtabliſhed a pein in this caſe, ſo that from henceforth for fear of the pein more than for fear of any Oath, they ſhall not ſpare any, nor conceal any Felonies; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth that Proclamation be ſolemnly made in all Counties, Hundreds, Markets, Fairs, and all other places where great Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort of People is, ſo that none ſhall excuſe themſelves by igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that from henceforth eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Country be ſo well kept, that immediately upon Felonies and Robberies committed, ſuch freſh ſuit be made from Town to Town, and from Country to Country, likewiſe when need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, that Inqueſt be made in Towns by him that is Lord of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:61578:51"/>the Town, and after in the Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and after in the Franchiſe, and in the County, and ſometime in two, three or four Counties; in caſe where Felonies be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the Marches of Shires, ſo that the Treſpaſſers may be attainted, and if the Country do not anſwer for ſuch manner of miſdoers, the pein ſhall be ſuch, that the Country, that is, the people dwelling in the Country, ſhall anſwer for the. Robberies done, and alſo for the damages, ſo that the whole Hundred where the Robbery happeneth to be done, with the Franchiſes, being within the precinct of the ſame Hundred, ſhall anſwer for the Robberies done; and if the Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery chance to be done in the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of two Hundreds, in ſuch caſe both Hundreds together, with the Franchiſes ſhall anſwer it; and after that the Felony or Robbery is done, the Country ſhall have no longer ſpace than forty days, within which it ſhall behoove them to agree for the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:61578:51"/>Robbery and Treſpaſs, or elſe that they anſwer for the Bodies of the Offenders; and foraſmuch as the King will not that his people ſhall be ſuddenly put in fear of this penalty, which ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth very hard to many, the King granteth that they ſhall not incur it immediately but it ſhall be reſpited untill the <hi>Eaſter</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" rend="italic" type="proclamation">
                  <head>Clauſ. Anno 21 <hi>Ed.</hi> 1. in 4. Dorſo.</head>
                  <head>Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio ſive Breve di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Vic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>. De quibuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuti pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamand<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>candis, &amp;c.</head>
                  <p>REX Vic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Eb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> s<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Cum ad ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jorem tranquilitatem p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrae tenend<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; depredatorum ac ali<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum malefactorum malitiam repri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendam quoſdam articulos ea occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione per totum Reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>um noſtru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>imus obſervera, inter quot ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>vimus &amp; mandavimus per ſingul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Comitatus infra idem Reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um quod
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:61578:52"/>ſtatim poſt Robberias &amp; Polonias fact as fieret recens ſecta de Villa in Villam &amp; de Patria in Patrium. Et ſimiliter Inquiſitiones fierent ſi neceſſe eſſet in Villis, Hundredis, Liberta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus, Comitatibus &amp; aliquando in duobus, tribus vel quatuor Comitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus in caſibus cum Feloniae factae fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſent in Marchia Comitatuum: Ita quod Malefactores deprehendi poſſent. Et ſi Patria de Corporibus hujuſmodi alefactorum non reſponderet, homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in Patria Commorantes de Robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riis factis &amp; damnis reſponderent, ac jam ex plurium inſinuatione acceperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus quod poſt Statutum &amp; Mandatum praedictum Homicidia, Robberiae, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendia &amp; aliae Trangreſſiones diverſae in Regno noſtro in defectum articulo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum praedictorum, minus plene obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatorum de die in diem plus ſolite perpetrantur. Nos hujuſmodi dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis &amp; periculis obviare volentes, mit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timus vobis Statutum illud per nos editum ſub ſigillo noſtro Praecipientes &amp; ſub gravi forisfactura noſtra fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miter injungentes quod omni dilatione praepoſitae Statutum praedictum in ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Comitatu tuo in ſingulis Hundredis,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:61578:52"/>Civitatibus, Burgis, Feriis, Mercatis, &amp; aliis locis ſolemnibus, quibus om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus &amp; ſingulis de Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> prad<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> inde major &amp; celerior notitia &amp; eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia fieri poterit publicé lege clamari &amp; firmiter teneri facias &amp; omnibus &amp; ſingulis contentis in eodem. Et pro certo ſcias &amp; univerſis &amp; ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis de Ballivae tua ex parte noſtra ſcire facias, quod exnunc conditiones &amp; poenas in dicto Statuto contentas de caetero volumus &amp; praecipimus firmiter teneri &amp; inviolabiliter obſervari. Et iſtud mandatum ita celeriter &amp; dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genter exequaris quod ad te &amp; tua tanquam ad mandatorum noſtrorum contemptorem graviter capere non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beamus. Teſte meipſo apud Weſtm<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> xviij. die Novembris.</p>
                  <p>Eodem modo mandatum eſt ſingulis Vic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> per totam Angliam per diverſa Mandata ſub tenore iſtius Literae prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedentis de verbo ad verbum, Teſte at ſupra.</p>
               </div>
               <div rend="margQuotes" type="statute">
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:61578:53"/>
                  <head>The Statute of <hi>28 Ed. 3.</hi> Cap. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>BEcauſe that great Clamour and grievous Complaints be made as well by Aliens as by Deniſens, the Merchants and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers paſſing through the Realm of <hi>England</hi> with their Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizes and other goods, be ſlain and robbed, and namely now more than they were wont, whereof remedy hath not been made to the Complainants; our Sovereign Lord the King conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the profit which may come to the ſaid Realm, by coming and abiding of Merchants Aliens in the ſame Realm, and the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and miſchief which to them and other is done daily by ſuch Manſlaughters and Robberies, and willing to provide for the ſurety and indemnity of Merchants and
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:61578:53"/>others aforeſaid, Hath ordained and eſtabliſhed, by the aſſent of all his Parliament, to the intent that Merchants Aliens ſhall have the greater will and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to come into the ſaid Realm of <hi>England,</hi> and that remedy from henceforth be ſpeedily made to ſuch Merchants and others robbed, according to the form contained in the Statute late made at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> that is to ſay, that ſolemn Cry be made in all Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Hundreds and Markets, Fairs and all other places where ſolemn aſſembly of the people ſhall be, ſo that none by ignorance ſhall excuſe him, that every Country from henceforth be ſo kept, that immediately after Felonies and Robberies done freſh ſuit be made from Town to Town, and from Country to Country, and Inqueſts, if need be, ſhall be alſo taken in the Towns by him which it Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign of the Town, and after in Hundreds, Franchiſes, and in the County, and ſometime in two, three or four Counties, in caſe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:61578:54"/>when Felonies ſhall be done in the Marches of the Counties, ſo that the Offenders may be attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and if the Country doth not anſwer of ſuch manner of Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, the pein ſhall be ſuch, that every Country, that is to ſay, the people dwelling in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, ſhall anſwer of the Robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries done, and of the damages, ſo that all the Hundred where the Robbery ſhall be done, with the Franchiſes which be within the precinct of the ſame Hundred, ſhall anſwer of the Robbery done; and if the Robbery be done in the Deviſes of two Hundreds, both Hundreds ſhall anſwer, together with the Franchiſes; and longer term ſhall not the Country have after the Robbery or Felony done than forty days, within which them behooveth to make gree of the Robbery or of the Offence, or that they anſwer of the Bodies of the Offenders.</p>
               </div>
               <div rend="margQuotes" type="statute">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:61578:54"/>
                  <head>The Statute of <hi>27 Eliz.</hi> Chap. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head>Of Huy and Cry.</head>
                  <p>WHereas by two ancient Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, the one made in the Parliament holden at <hi>Winche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> in the thirteenth year of the reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt, and the other in the eight and twentieth year of the reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, it was, for the better ſuppreſſing of Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries and Felonies (amongſt other things) enacted to this effect, That if the Country do not anſwer for the bodies of ſuch Malefactours, that then the pein ſhould be ſuch, that is to wit, That the people dwelling in the Country, ſhall be anſwerable for the Robberies done, and the da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages: ſo that the whole Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred where the Robbery ſhall be
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:61578:55"/>done, with the Franchiſes which are within the precinct of the ſame Hundred, ſhall anſwer the Robberies done. And if the Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery chance to be done in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion of two Hundreds, that then both the Hundreds together, with the Franchiſes within the precinct of them, ſhall be anſwerable, as in the ſaid two ſeveral Statutes it doth more at large appear. Foraſmuch as the ſaid parts of the ſaid ſeveral Statutes being of late days more commonly put in execution than heretofore they have been, are found by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to be very hard and extreme to many of the Queens Majeſties good Subjects, becauſe by the ſame Statutes they do remain charged with the penalties there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in contained, notwithſtanding their unability to ſatisfie the ſame, and though they doe as much as in reaſon might be required in purſuing ſuch Malefactours and Offenders, whereby both large ſcope of negligence is given to the Inhabitants and Reſiants in
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:61578:55"/>other Hundreds and Counties, not to proſecute the Huy and Cry made, followed and brought unto them, by reaſon they are not chargeable for any portion of the goods robbed, nor with any damages in that behalf gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and alſo great incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and imboldening is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe given unto the Offenders to commit daily more Felonies and Robberies, as ſeeing it in manner impoſſible for the Inhabitants and Reſiants of the ſaid Hundred and Franchiſes wherein the Robbery is committed, to apprehend them without the aid of the other Hundreds and Counties adjoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and for that alſo that the party robbed having remedy by the aforeſaid Statutes, for the recovering of his goods robbed, and damages againſt the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants and reſiants of the Hundred wherein the Robbery was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, is many times negligent and careleſs in proſecuting and purſuing the ſaid Malefactours and Offenders: Our Sovereign
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:61578:56"/>Lady the Queens Majeſty, not willing therefore that her people ſhould be impoveriſhed by any ſuch pein or penalty, which ſhould be hard or grievous to them, and have ſpecial regard to abate the power of Felons, and to repreſs Felonies, doth for remedy here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, with the conſent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and of the Commons of this preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by the authority of the ſame Parliament eſtabliſh and enact, That the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants and Reſiants of every or any ſuch Hundred,<note place="margin">Hundred.</note> (with the Franchiſes within the precinct thereof) wherein negligence, fault or defect of purſuit, and freſh ſuit,<note place="margin">Freſh ſuit. Huy and Cry.</note> after Huy and Cry made, ſhall happen to be, from and after forty days next after the end of this preſent Seſſion of Parliament,<note place="margin">Moiety.</note> ſhall anſwer and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie the one moiety or half of all and every ſuch ſum and ſums of money and damages, as ſhall by force or virtue of the ſaid Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes or either of them be reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:61578:56"/>or had, againſt or of the ſaid Hundred, with the Franchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes therein, in which any Robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or Felony ſhall at any time hereafter be committed or done. And that the ſame moiety ſhall and may be recovered by Action of Debt, Bill, Plaint or Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, in any of the Queens Majeſties Courts of Record at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> by and in the name of the Clerk of the Peace for the time being,<note place="margin">Clerk of the Peace.</note> of or in any ſuch County within this Realm, where any ſuch Robbery and recovery by the party or parties robbed ſhall be, without naming the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian name or Sirname of the ſaid Clerk of the Peace, which moie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſo recovered, ſhall be to the onely uſe and behoof of the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the ſaid Hundred, where any ſuch Robbery or Felony ſhall be committed or done. And be it further enacted by the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty aforeſaid, That if any Clerk of the Peace, of or in any Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty within this Realm ſhall at any time hereafter commence
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:61578:57"/>or prefer any ſuch Suit, Action, or Information, and ſhall after the ſame ſo ſued, commenced, or preferred, happen to die, or to be removed out of his Office, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore recovery and execution had: That yet no ſuch Action; Suit, Bill, Plaint or Information, ſued, commenced, or preferred, ſhall by ſuch diſplacing or death, be abated, diſcontinued or ended, but that it ſhall and may be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to and for the Clerk of the Peace next ſucceeding in the ſaid County, to proſecute, purſue and follow all and every ſuch Action, Bill, Plaint, Suit and Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for the cauſes aforeſaid, ſo hanging and depending in ſuch manner and form, and to all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and purpoſes, as that Clerk of Peace might have done which firſt commenced or preferred the ſaid Suit, Bill, Plaint or Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And although the whole Hundred where ſuch Robberies and Felonies are committed, with the Liberties within the precinct thereof, are by the two former
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:61578:57"/>Statutes charged with the anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to the party robbed his da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages: yet nevertheleſs the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery and execution, by and for the party and parties robbed, is had againſt one, or a very few perſons of the ſaid Inhabitants, and he and they ſo charged, have not heretofore by Law had any mean or way to have any contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of or from the reſidue of the ſaid Hundred,<note place="margin">Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> where the ſaid Robbery is committed, to the great impoveriſhing of them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom ſuch recovery or execution is had. For remedy whereof, be it enacted by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority aforeſaid, That after ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of damages by the party or parties ſo robbed had, it ſhall and may be lawfull (upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint made by the party or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſo charged) to and for two Juſtices of the Peace,<note place="margin">Juſt. of P.</note> (whereof one to be of the <hi>Quorum</hi>) of the ſame County, inhabiting within the ſaid Hundred, or near unto the ſame, where any ſuch execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be had, to aſſeſs and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:61578:58"/>tax ratably and proportionably,<note place="margin">Tax.</note> according to their diſcretions, all and every the Towns, Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes, Villages and Hamlets, as well of the ſaid Hundred where any ſuch Robbery ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, as of the Liberties with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſaid Hundred, to and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards an equal contribution to be had and made for the relief of the ſaid Inhabitant or Inhabitants, againſt whom the party or par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties robbed before that time had his or their execution: And that after ſuch taxation made, the Conſtables,<note place="margin">Conſtables. Headbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs.</note> Conſtable, Headbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs or Headborough of every ſuch Town, Pariſh, Village and Hamlet, ſhall by virtue of this preſent act, have full power and authority within their ſeveral limits, ratably and proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably to tax and aſſeſs according to their abilities,<note place="margin">Tax.</note> every Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant and dweller in every ſuch Town, Pariſh, Village and Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, for and towards the payment of ſuch taxation and aſſeſſment as ſhall be ſo made, upon every ſuch
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:61578:58"/>Town, Pariſh, Village and Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let as aforeſaid, by the ſaid Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices: and that if any Inhabitant of any ſuch Town, Pariſh, Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage or Hamlet, ſhall obſtinately refuſe and deny to pay the ſaid taxation and aſſeſſment,<note place="margin">Refuſe.</note> ſo by the ſaid Conſtables, Conſtable, Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boroughs or Headborough taxed and aſſeſſed, that then it ſhall and may be lawfull to and for the ſaid Conſtables and Headboroughs, and every of them within their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral limits and juriſdictions,<note place="margin">Diſtrein.</note> to diſtrein all and every ſuch per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and perſons ſo refuſing and denying by his and their goods and chattels, and the ſame diſtreſs to ſell, and the money thereof coming to retain to the uſe afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. And if the goods and chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tels ſo diſtreined and ſold, ſhall be of more value than the ſaid taxation ſhall come unto, that then the reſidue of the ſaid money over and above the ſaid taxation ſhall be delivered unto the ſaid perſon and perſons ſo diſtreined. And be it further enacted, that
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:61578:59"/>all and every the ſaid Conſtables and Headboroughs,<note place="margin">Conſtables. Headbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughs.</note> after that they have within their ſeveral li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits and juriſdictions levied and collected their ſaid rates and ſums of money ſo taxed, ſhall within ten days after ſuch collection pay and deliver the ſame over unto the ſaid Juſtices of Peace, or one of them, to the uſe and behoof of the ſaid Inhabitant or Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, for whom ſuch rate, taxa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and aſſeſſment ſhall be had or made as aforeſaid: which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney ſo paid, ſhall by the Juſtices or Juſtice ſo receiving the ſame, be delivered over (upon requeſt made) unto the ſaid Inhabitant or Inhabitants, to whoſe uſe the ſame was collected. And be it further enacted by the authority aforeſaid, that the like taxati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, aſſeſſment, levying by diſtreſs and payment as aforeſaid, ſhall be had and done within every Hundred where default or negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence of purſuit and freſh fuit ſhall be,<note place="margin">Hundreds.</note> for and to the benefit of all and every Inhabitant and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:61578:59"/>Inhabitants of the ſame Hundred, where ſuch default ſhall be, that ſhall at any time hereafter by virtue of this preſent Act, have any damages or money levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of them, for or to the pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the one moiety or half of the money recovered againſt the ſaid Hundred, where any Robbery ſhall be hereafter com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. Provided, alſo, and be it further enacted by the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty aforeſaid, that where any Robbery is,<note place="margin">Robbery.</note> or ſhall be hereafter committed by two, or a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter number of Malefactours, and that it happen any one of the ſaid Offenders to be apprehended by purſuit to be made according to the ſaid former mentioned Laws and Statutes,<note place="margin">Offenden taken.</note> or according to this preſent Act, that then and in ſuch caſe, no Hundred or Franchiſe ſhall in any wiſe incur, or fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the penalty, loſs or forfeiture mentioned either in this preſent Act, or in the ſaid former Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, although the reſidue of the ſaid Malefactours ſhall happen to
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:61578:60"/>eſcape, and not to be apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: any thing in this Statute, or in the ſaid former Statute to the contrary notwithſtanding. Provided alſo, that no perſon or perſons hereafter robbed ſhall take any benefit by virtue of any the ſaid former Statutes, to charge any Hundred where any ſuch Robbery ſhall be committed, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he or they ſo robbed, ſhall commence his or their Suit or Action within one year next after ſuch Robbery ſo to be committed.<note place="margin">One year.</note> And be it further enacted by the authority aforeſaid, that no Huy or Cry, or purſuit hereafter to be done or made by the Country or Inhabitants of any Hundred, ſhall be allowed and taken to be a lawfull Huy and Cry, or purſuit, upon or after any the ſaid Felons or Offenders, except the ſame Huy and Cry and purſuit be done and made by Horſemen and Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">Horſemen. and Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</note> any uſage or cuſtom to the contrary notwithſtanding. And be it further alſo enacted by the authority of this preſent Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:61578:60"/>that no perſon or perſons that ſhall hereafter happen to be robbed, ſhall have or maintain any Action, or take any benefit by virtue of the ſaid two mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Statutes, or either of them, except the ſaid perſon and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo robbed, ſhall with as much convenient ſpeed as may be, give notice and intelligence of the ſaid Felony or Robbery ſo commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, unto ſome of the Inhabitants of ſome Town, Village or Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let near unto the place where any ſuch Robbery ſhall be committed, nor ſhall bring or have any Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, upon or by virtue of any the Statutes aforeſaid, except he or they ſhall firſt within twenty days next before ſuch Action to be brought, be examined upon his or their corporal Oath,<note place="margin">Oath.</note> to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken before ſome one Juſtice of the Peace of the County, where the Robbery was committed, inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biting within the ſaid Hundred where the Robbery was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or near unto the ſame, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he or they do know the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:61578:61"/>that committed the ſaid Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, or any of them. And if upon ſuch examination it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed that he or they do know the parties that committed the ſaid Robbery, or any of them, that then he or they ſo confeſſing ſhall before the ſaid Action be commenced or brought, enter into ſufficient bond by Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance before the ſaid Juſtice,<note place="margin">Recogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom the ſaid examination is had, effectually to proſecute the ſame perſon and perſons ſo known to have committed the ſaid Robbery, by Indictment or otherwiſe, according to the due courſe of the Laws of this Realm. <bibl>
                        <hi>Anno</hi> 27 <hi>Eliz</hi> cap. 13.</bibl>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:61578:61"/>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="case_law">
               <head>Judicial proceedings on the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Huy and Cry, or choice Precedents in all caſes therein from the Original to Execution.</head>
               <div xml:lang="lat" rend="italic" type="document">
                  <head>Breve ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginale ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Statut<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de Hutes<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; Clam<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <signed>CArolus Secundus, Dei gratia, Angliae, Scotiae, Franciae &amp; Hiberniae Rex, Fidei defenſor, &amp;c.</signed>
                     <salute>Vic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> D. ſalutem,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>ſi A. B. nuper de C. in Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> tuo gen<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> fec<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> te ſecur<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de Clam<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſuo pros<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> tunc Pone per vad<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; ſalvos pleg<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Homines Inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Hundred<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de O. in Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> tuo quòd ſint coram, &amp;c. (tali Retorn<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>) oſtens<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re cum in Statuto in Parliamento Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini Edwardi nuper Regis Angliae primi apud Winton<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> anno regni ſui tertiodecimo tent<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> edit<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> (inter cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tera) ordinat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſit pro eo quòd de die in diem Roberiae, Homicidia &amp; In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendia plus ſolito tunc fiebant quàm antea ſolebant &amp; Felones non potuiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent eſſe attinct<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> per ſacrm<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Jur<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> qui magis voluntarie permittebant Felonias fieri de gentibus extraneis, &amp; Felones
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:61578:62"/>evadere abſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> poena quàm Malefacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res indictari, unde magna pars fuerunt gentes de eadem Patria, vel adminus ſi Malefactores fuerunt de alia Patria eorum Receptores fuerunt de Viſneto ubi hujusmodi malefacta fiebant. Et hoc faciebant pro eo quod ſacrm<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> eiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem Juratoribus non miniſtrabantur nec in Patria ubi Feloniae illae fiebant &amp; quoad reſtitutionem damnorum poena antetunc non fuit provis<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> pro concelamento &amp; negligentia fuis. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem nuper Rex ad debilitand<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> poſſe Felonum ſtabilivit poenam in illo caſu. Ita quòd pro timore poenae pluſquam pro pavore Sacramenti nullis extunc parcerent nec aliquas Felonias conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larent. Et mandavit quòd Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matio ſolemniter fieret in omnibus Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Hundred<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Mercat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Feriis &amp; omnibus aliis locis ubi ſolemnis aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blaiio gentium foret ſic quod nullus pro ignorantia ſe poſſit excuſare. Et quod quaelibet Patria extunc ſic poſſit cuſtodiri quod immediate poſt Roberias &amp; Felonias factas recens inſecutio fieret de Villa in Villam &amp; de Patria in Patriam ac etiam Inquiſitiones fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> neceſſe foret in Villis per ipſum
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:61578:62"/>qui ſuperior eſſet de Villa. Et poſtea in Hundred<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Franches<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; in Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>. Et aliquando in duobus, tribus vel quatuor Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in caſu quando Feloniae fact<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> fuer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Marchiis Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ita quod Malefactores potuiſſent eſſe attinct<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>. Et ſi Patria de hujuſmodi Malefacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus non reſponderet poena talis eſſet quod quaelibet Patria ſcilicet homines in Patria commorantes reſponderent de Roberiis factis &amp; damnis ſic quod totum Hundredum ubi Roberia illa facta foret cum Franches<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> quae eſſent infra praecinct<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ejuſdem Hundred<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponderent de Roberiis, factis. Et ſi Roberia illa facta foret in diviſis duo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Hundred<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> reſponderent inde duo Hundred<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> cum Franches<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>. Et longio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem terminum non haberet Patria poſt Roberiam &amp; Felonias factas quam quadraginta dies infra quos faceret emendas de Roberia &amp; malefactis vel reſponderet de corporibus Malefacto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum prout in Statuto plenius contine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Ac cum quidam Malefactores prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> A. B. ignoti in quodam loco ibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem vocat. B. infra Hundred<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de O. in Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> tuo vi &amp; armis, &amp;c. in ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum A. B. inſultum fecer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; 20li.
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:61578:63"/>in pecuniis numeratis de denariis ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius A. B. propriis ibidem invent<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de codem A. B. Felonice perceperunt, ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaverunt &amp; aſportaverunt contra pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem noſtram. Idemque A. B. imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate poſt Feloniam, Roberiam &amp; ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liationem praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> fact<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> apud B. praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> infra Hundred<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de O. praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Hutes<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; Clam<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de Roberia &amp; Felonia praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> fecit &amp; adtunc notitiam ibidem In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ejuſdem Villae de O. praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de Roberia &amp; Felonia praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> fact<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> dedit. Et poſt Roberiam &amp; Feloniam ill<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ac infra <hi>20</hi> dies ante diem impetratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis brevis original<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>. Idem A. B. coram E. F. Ar<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> tunc uno Juſtic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> noſtrorum ad pacem in praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> D. conſervand<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> aſſign<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> apud L. prope praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Hundred<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de O. praed. in Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> tuo examinat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> fuit ſuper ſacrm<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſuum corporale juxta formam Statuti apud Weſtm<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> anno regni Dominae Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabethae nuper Reginae Angliae viceſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ſeptimo inde edit<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; provis<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>. I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demque A. B. ſuper ſacrm<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſuum praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> tunc dixit quod ipſe non cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novit partes quae Roberiam illam fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſent nec earum aliquam. Et poſt Roberiam illam factam quadraginta
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:61578:63"/>dies jam praterierunt. Iidem tamen homines inhabitantes in Hundred<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Emendas de Roberia praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> A. B. hucuſque non fecerunt nec corpora Felonum &amp; Malefactorum praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> nec corpus eorum alicujus cepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt nec de corporibus eorum ſeu de corpore eorum alicujus hucuſque re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponderunt ſed Malefactores &amp; Felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ill<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> evadere permiſerunt in noſtri contemptum &amp; ipſius A. B. grave damnum &amp; contra formam Statuti praedicti de anno tertiodecimo ſupra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicto. Et habeas ibi nomina Pleg<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>&amp; hoc breve Teſte meipſo apud Weſtm<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>, &amp;c.</dateline>
                     <signed>Plegii de pros<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>J. Doo</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>R. Roo</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
Sum<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> infra nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Hundred<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de <hi>O.</hi> in Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> infra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript.<note place="margin">Retorn<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> inde.</note>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
                  <trailer>
                     <hi>G. H.</hi> Ar<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Vic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" rend="italic" type="document">
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:61578:64"/>
                  <head>Narr<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> inde.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>Devon<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> 
                        <hi>ſſ.</hi>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>HOmines inhabitantes in Hundredo de O. in Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> praedicto attach<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> fuer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ad reſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dend<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> A. B. gen<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de p<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>lito quare cum in Statuto in Parliamento, &amp;c. (ut ſupra uſque) vel reſponderet de cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poribus Malefactorum prout in Statu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to praedicto plenius continetur: as cum quidam Malefactores praefato A. ignoti apud O. in Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> praedicto in quodam loco ibidem vocat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> B. (ut ſupra uſque) &amp; contra formam Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuti praedicti, &amp;c. Et unde idem A. per G. F. Attorn<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſuum queri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur quod cum quidam Malefactores videlicet quatuor Homines eidem A. ignot<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> 
                     <hi>19</hi> die J. anno Regni dict<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini Regis nunc <hi>33</hi> apud O. in Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> praedicto in quodam loco ibidem vocat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> B. &amp;c. (ut ſupra uſque) Et poſt Roberiam &amp; Feloniam ill<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> fact<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; infra <hi>20</hi> dies prox<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ante diem impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trationis brevis originalis praedicti A. ſcilicet <hi>20</hi> die J. anno Regni Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini Regis nune <hi>33</hi> praedictus A. coram praedicto E. F. Ar. tunc uno Juſtic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>, &amp;c. (ut ſupra uſque) Et poſt Roberiam illam fact<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; ante
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:61578:64"/>diem impetrationis brevis originalis praedicti A. <hi>40</hi> dies jam ſcilicet die impetrationis brevis originalis ipſius A. praeterierunt, &amp;c. (ut ſupra uſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que) contra formam Statuti praedicti, unde dic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> quod deteriorat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> eſt &amp; dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num habet ad valenc<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>, &amp;c. Et inde produc<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſectam, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Aliter in diviſis Hundre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorum.</note>
                     <hi>ſſ.</hi> HOmines inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> infra Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de A. &amp; B. in Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> praedicto attach<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> fuer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ad reſpondend<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> tam Domino Regi nunc quàm C. D. gen<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de p<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>lito quare cum in Statuto (ut in Or<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> uſque) ac cum quidam Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefactores praefat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> C. ignot<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Regia via infra parochiam de B. in Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> praedicto (quae quidem Regia via eſt in diviſis Hundredorum) vi &amp; armis (ut in Or<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> uſque) Idemque C. imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate poſt Feloniam, &amp;c. fact<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> apud Villam de H. in praedicto com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> M. (quae quidem Villa de H. eſt prope praedictum locum ubi Roberia praedicta ſic ut praefertur facta fuit) Hutes<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; Clam<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de Roberia &amp; Felonia praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> fecit. Et adtunc &amp; ibidem notitiam inhabitantibus ejuſdem Villae de H. de Roberia &amp; Felonia illis dedit, &amp;c. (ut in Or<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>.)</p>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" rend="italic" type="proceedings">
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:61578:65"/>
                  <head>Barr<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſur Statut<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de Hutes<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; Clam<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>.</head>
                  <div type="document">
                     <head>Non cul. ove chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge de Hundred<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ſſ.</hi> ET praedicti homines inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Hundredo praedicto per A. B. Attorn<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſuum ven<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; defend<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> vim &amp; injur<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; omnem contemptum. Et quicquid, &amp;c. Et dic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> quod ipſi in nullo ſunt culpabiles de premiſſis ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius eis impoit<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> contra formam Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuti praedicti prout praedictus quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſuperius verſus eos queritur. Et de hoc pon<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſe ſuper Patriam &amp; prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictus quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſimiliter. Et ſuper hoc idem quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> dic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> quod praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> homines inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in praedicto Hundredo de W. ubi Roberia illa facta fuit ſunt partes defendentes verſus quos idem quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in forma praedicta queritur. Et ea de cauſa pet<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> breve Domini Regis Vic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> dirigend<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de venire faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> hic duodecim, &amp;c. de Viſn<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Hundredi de O. praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> (quod quidem Hundredum de O. eſt prox<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Hundredum in eodem Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> praedict<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Hundredo de W. prox<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacen<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>)
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:61578:65"/>ad triand<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> exitum praedictum ſuperius in forma praedicta junct<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>. Et quia homines inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in praedicto Hundredo de W. hoc non dedic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ei conceditur, &amp;c.<note place="margin">Verdict &amp; Judgment pur le pl<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>t.</note> Ideo praecept<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> eſt Vic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> quod venire fac<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> hic in Craſtino ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae Trin<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de Viſn<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de praedicto Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dr<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de O. duodecim, &amp;c. per quos, &amp;c. Et qui nec, &amp;c. ad recogn<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>, &amp;c. quia tam, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="document">
                     <head>Barr<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> per nul Huy &amp; Cry fait.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ſſ.</hi> ET praedicti inhabitantes per A. B. attorn<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſuum ven<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> vim &amp; injur<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; omnem con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptum. Et quicquid, &amp;c. Et dic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> quod praedictus quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Quia prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtando quod praedictus quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> non ſpolia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus fuit Proteſtandoque etiam quod praedictus quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> per ſpoliationem prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictam non perdidit aliqua bona ſive catalla vel pecuniarum ſummas prout praedictus quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſuperius allegavit. Pro placito iidem inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> dicunt quod praedictus quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> immediate poſt Feloniam, Roberiam &amp; ſpoliationem praedictas ſuperius fieri ſuppoſit<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> apud A. praedict<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> non fecit Huteſiam &amp; Clamorem de Roberia praedicta ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum formam Statuti praedicti prout
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:61578:66"/>ipſe ſuperius allegavit. Et hoc para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ſunt verificare unde petunt Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium ſi praedictus quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> actionem ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am praedictam verſus eos habere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beat, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="document">
                     <head>Non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſur Star. de Huy &amp; Cry, ove Judgment puis brief de Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ſſ.</hi> ET praedicti homines inhabitan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes in Hundredo praedicto per C. D. attorn<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſuum ven<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; defend<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> vim &amp; injur<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> quando, &amp;c. Et quic-quid, &amp;c. Et idem attorn<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> dic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> quod ipſe non eſt inform<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> per eoſdem homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Hundredo praedicto de aliquo Reſpons<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> pro eiſdem hominibus inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Hundredo praedicto prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in loquela praedicta dand<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>. Et nihil aliud inde dic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> per quod idem quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> reman<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> verſas praefat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Hundredo prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicto inde indefens<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ob quod praedictus quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> damna ſua occaſione prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſa verſus praefat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> homines inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Hundredo praedicto recupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare debeat, ſed quia neſcitur quae dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na idem quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſuſtinuit occaſione illa praeceptum eſt Vic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> quod per Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum proborum &amp; legalium homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num de Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> praedicto diligenter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirat quae damna idem quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſuſtinuit
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:61578:66"/>tam occaſione praemiſſa quàm pro mis<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; cuſtagiis ſuis per ipſum circa ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam ſuam in hac parte appoſit<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>. Et Inquiſitionem quam, &amp;c. Vic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtare fac<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> hic à die Paſche in quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decim dies ſub ſigillo, &amp;c. Et ſigil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, &amp;c. Et Vic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> videlicet A. B. Ar<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> modo mand<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> hic quandam Inquiſitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem coram eo apud Brentford in Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> praedicto (tali die &amp; Menſe) ult<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> praeterit<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> per ſacrm<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> duodecim, &amp;c. virtute brevis praedicti capt<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> per quam compert<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> exiſtit quod praedictus quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſuſtinuit damna occaſione praemiſſa ultra mis<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; cuſtagia ſua per ipſum circa ſectam ſuam in hac parte ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſit<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ad triginta libras. Et pro mis<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; cuſtagiis illis ad decem ſolid<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>. Id<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eo cons<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> eſt quod praedictus quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuperet verſus praefat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> homines inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Hundredo praedicto damna ſua praedicta ad triginta libras &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem ſolidos per Inquiſitionem praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctam in forma praedicta compert<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non duodecim libras eidem quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ad requiſitionem ſuam pro miſis &amp; cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtagiis ſuis praedictis per Cur<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> hic de inc<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>ro adjudicat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>. Que quidem dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na in toto ſe attingunt ad quadra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginta
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:61578:67"/>duas libras &amp; decem denar<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>. Et praedicti homines inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Hundredo praedicto in mia<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="document">
                     <head>Judgment ſur Statute de Hue &amp; Cry puis Verdict.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ſſ.</hi> I Deo cons<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> eſt quod praedictus quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> recuperet verſus praefat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> homines inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Hundredo prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicto damna ſua praedicta ad, &amp;c. per Jur<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> praedictos in forma praedicta aſſeſs<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> necnon, &amp;c. eidem quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> qui tam, &amp;c. ad requiſitionem ſuam pro mis<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; cuſtagiis ſuis praedictis per Cur<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> hic de inc<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>ro adjudicat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>. Que quidem damna in toto ſe attingunt ad, &amp;c. Et praedicti homines inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in mia<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="lat" rend="italic" type="proceedings">
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:61578:67"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Venire Facias</hi> upon the Statute of Huy and Cry.</head>
                  <div type="document">
                     <head>Ven<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Fac<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ſſ.</hi> PRaecip<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> tibi quod Ven<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Fac<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, &amp;c. duodecim liberos &amp; legales homines de Viſn<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Hundred<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de O. in Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> D. quorum quilibet habeat 4li. terr<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>, &amp;c. per quos, &amp;c. Et qui nec A. B. qui tam pro nobis quam pro ſeipſo ſequit<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> quer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> nec ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Hundredo de O. in Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> D. aliqua affinitate attingunt ad faciend<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> quandam Jur<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> inter par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de placito tranſgr<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> contra formam Stat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de Hutes<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; Clam<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in hujuſmodi caſu inde nuper edit<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; provis<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> quia tam iidem homines inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Hundre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> quam nos &amp; praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> R. inter quos inde contentio eſt poſuer<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſe in jurat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> illam. Et habeas ibi nomina Jur<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; hoc breve T. &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="document">
                     <head>Diſtr<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Jur<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>ſſ.</hi> PRaecip<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> tibi quod diſtr<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> homines inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Hundred<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de O. in Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> tuo per omnes, &amp;c. ita quod
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:61578:68"/>habeas corpora eorum coram, &amp;c. ad reſp<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> tam nobis quam A. B. quare cum in Statuo in Parliamento Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini Edvardi nuper Regis Angliae, primi (ut in Or<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> uſque) &amp; contra formam Statuti de anno <hi>13.</hi> praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>. Et ad audiend<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> judicium ſuum de plur<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> defalt<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>. Et habeat, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Retorn<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>.</note> Manucapt<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> infra nominat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> hominum inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Hundred<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de O. infra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcript<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>
                           <list>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>J. Doo</hi>
                              </item>
                              <item>
                                 <hi>R. Roo</hi>
                              </item>
                              <trailer>Exit<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> xli.</trailer>
                           </list>
                        </signed>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>E. H.</hi> Ar<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Vic<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="document">
                     <head>Inquir<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de dais in Tranſgr. &amp; contempt<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſur Stat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de Hutes<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; Clam<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>SAlutem. </salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>Cum homines inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Hundred<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de O. in Com<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> tuo attach<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> eſſent eſſend<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> in Cur<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> noſtra coram, &amp;c. ad reſpondend<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> tam nob<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> quam R. B. de placito quare cum in Statuto in Parliamento Domini Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vardi, &amp;c. Et contra formam Statu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de anno <hi>13.</hi> praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Taliter<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> in Cur<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> noſtra coram, &amp;c. proceſs<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> eſt quod praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> R. damna ſua occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:61578:68"/>praemiſſa verſus praefat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> homines inhabitan<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> infra praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Hundred<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> de O. recuperare debeat. Et quia Cur<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> noſtra incognit<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> exiſtit que damna praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> R. tam occaſione praemiſs<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> quam pro mis<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; cuſtagiis ſuis per ipſum circa ſectam ſuam in hac parte appoſit<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſuſtinuit tibi praecipimus quod per ſacr<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>m proborum &amp; legalium ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum de balliva tua diligent<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras quae damna praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> R. tam occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione praemiſs<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> quam pro mis<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> &amp; cuſtagiis ſuis praed<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſuſtinuit. Et Inquiſitionem ill<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſic per te diſtincte &amp; aperte capt<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> Nob<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> ſub ſigillo tuo &amp; ſigillis eorum per quorum ſacr<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>m Inquiſition<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> illam feceris in (tali Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torn<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>) ubicunque tunc fuerimus in Anglia mittas una cum hoc brevi Teſte, &amp;c.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="sample_deposition">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:61578:69"/>
               <head>The Oath to be taken before a Juſtice of the Peace by the perſon or perſons who were rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed whereupon the party rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed may ground his Action, according to the Statute of <hi>27 Eliz.</hi>
               </head>
               <opener>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>The</hi> 20th <hi>day of</hi> January, 1681.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </opener>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mid<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>
                  </hi> THE day and year above-ſaid <hi>A. B.</hi> of <hi>C.</hi> in the County of <hi>D.</hi> Gent. came before <hi>E. F.</hi> 
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> one of his Majeſties Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Peace in the ſaid County of <hi>D.</hi> and made Oath, That Monday morning, being the 19th day of this inſtant <hi>January,</hi> about 8 of the Clock, the ſaid <hi>A. B.</hi> and one <hi>L. M.</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> Merchant, came from <hi>B.</hi> where they lay the night before at the Sign of the <hi>King<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>s Head</hi> there, and dined at <hi>C.</hi> at the <hi>Queen<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>s Head</hi> there, and about two of the Clock went from thence to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:61578:69"/>
                  <hi>D.</hi> and about five or ſix miles off from the Town, there overtook them in the High-way, between a place called <hi>Johnſon</hi>
                  <g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>s Oak and the Park Wall of <hi>L. T.</hi>
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr> four Horſemen, one where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (deſcribing them by their Perſons, Habits and Horſes) which ſaid four Horſemen ſet upon this Examinant and robbed him, taking from him by force the Sum of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the ſaid <hi>A. B.</hi> being examined whether he knoweth the ſaid par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or any of them which ſo rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed him, he ſaith and depoſeth that he doth not know them or any of them.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>A. B.</signed>
               </closer>
               <postscript>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Jurat<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g> die &amp; anno ſupra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict<g ref="char:abbrapo">’</g>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>coram me E. F.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </postscript>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:61578:70" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Catalogue of Books ſold by</hi> Langley Curtis, <hi>at the Sign of Sir</hi> Edmundbury Godfrey'<hi>s</hi> Head <hi>in</hi> Goat Court <hi>on</hi> Lud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate-Hill.</head>
            <list>
               <item>THE <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of the <hi>Damnable Popiſh Plot.</hi> Written by the Authour of <hi>The weekly Pacquet of Advice from Rome.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Reign</hi> of King <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard</hi> the Second. By a Perſon of Quality.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Popery;</hi> or, The <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Poſitions</hi> approved by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (when really believ'd and practis'd) are very dangerous to all, and to <hi>Proteſtant Kings</hi> more eſpecially, and inconſiſtent with Loyalty. By <hi>T.</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Supplications</hi> of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the <hi>Life</hi> of Sir <hi>Edmundbury
<pb facs="tcp:61578:70"/>Godfrey,</hi> with <hi>Private</hi> and <hi>Family Devotions;</hi> alſo <hi>Prayers</hi> againſt <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> with <hi>Thanksgivings</hi> and <hi>Graces.</hi> By <hi>Henry Godfrey,</hi> M. A.</item>
               <item>A Compendious <hi>Treatiſe</hi> of <hi>Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries</hi> upon Writs of Entry in the Poſt, and Fines upon Writs of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, with ample inſtructions how to draw, acknowledge and levy the ſame in all Caſes.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Aſtrological Judgment</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>Phyſick,</hi> deduced from the Poſition of the Heavens at the Decumbiture of the Sick Perſon, ſhewing by an univerſal Method, not onely the Cauſe, but the Cure and End of all manner of Diſeaſes incident to humane Bodies: being the thirty years Practice and Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of <hi>Richard Saunders,</hi> Student in <hi>Aſtrology</hi> and <hi>Phyſick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>England</hi>'s <hi>Remarques,</hi> giving an exact account of the ſeveral Shires, Counties and Iſlands in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales,</hi> how Bounded, their Length, Breadth and Circumference; the temperature of the Air, and ferti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity or barrenneſs of Soil; the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities they afford; the Dioceſes,
<pb facs="tcp:61578:71"/>Pariſhes, Parliament Men, Hundreds and Markets; and whatever elſe is remarkable throughout the whole Kingdom.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Proteſtant School,</hi> or <hi>Forms of Prayer, Pſalms, Leſſons, Thanksgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings</hi> and <hi>Graces,</hi> for the bringing up and well-grounding Children and elder Perſons in the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi> By Biſhop <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher.</hi> Alſo a Catalogue of all <hi>Engliſh</hi> Words, from one to eight Syllables, divided and not divided, teaching the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt way to Spell, Reade and Write <hi>true Engliſh.</hi> To which is added, an <hi>Hiſtorical Account</hi> of ſeveral <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>remarkable Paſſages,</hi> lively repreſented in <hi>Copper Plates.</hi> By <hi>Moſes Lane,</hi> Schoolmaſter in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An <hi>Alarm for Sinners;</hi> or the <hi>Confeſſion, Prayers, Letters</hi> and <hi>laſt words</hi> of Mr. <hi>Foulkes,</hi> late Miniſter of <hi>Stanton-Lacy.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Character</hi> of an <hi>Ill-Court-Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite,</hi> repreſenting the <hi>Michiefs</hi> that flow from <hi>Miniſters of State</hi> when they are more <hi>great</hi> than <hi>good.</hi> Tranſlated out of <hi>French.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:61578:71"/>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Turbulent;</hi> or, the <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholicks:</hi> a Comedy, as it was acted at the <hi>Duke's Theatre.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The <hi>Medal Revers'd;</hi> a <hi>Satyr</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Perſecution.</hi> By the Authour of <hi>Azaria</hi> and <hi>Huſhai.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Azaria</hi> and <hi>Huſhai;</hi> a Poem.</item>
               <item>The <hi>Clerk</hi>'s <hi>Manual;</hi> or, an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act Collection of the moſt approved Forms of Declarations, Pleas, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Iſſues, Judgments, Demurrers, and moſt kind of Writs now uſed in the Court of <hi>Kings Bench,</hi> with neceſſary inſtructions to all <hi>Clerks, Attorneys, Sollicitours,</hi> &amp;c. in the uſe of the ſame.</item>
               <item>The plain <hi>Engliſhman</hi>'s <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> or, a Compendious Chronicle of <hi>England,</hi> from its firſt being inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited to this preſent year, 1679. But more eſpecially containing the chief Remarques of all our Kings and Queens ſince the Conqueſt, their Lives and Reigns, Policies, Wars, Laws, Succeſſes and Troubles: With the moſt notable Accidents, as Dearths, Tempeſts, Monſtrous Births, and other Prodigies that happened in each of their times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:61578:72"/>
               <item>A <hi>Synopſis</hi> of <hi>Heraldry;</hi> or, The moſt plain, ſhort and eaſie way for the perfect attaining of that Art, containing all neceſſary directions in order thereunto: There being about 300 Coats of Arms, and about 50 Creſts engraven upon Copper Plates; and the Atchievements of the Kings of <hi>England</hi> ſince King <hi>Egbert</hi> of the Saxon Race. The Paternal Coats of the Nobility of <hi>England</hi> [with a Liſt of the Knights of the Garter] The Arms of the Archiepiſcopal and Epiſcopal Sees, and of the two Univerſities, and the ſeveral Colleges in them; and of the Inns of Court, and other Houſes of Law in <hi>London;</hi> with ſome hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of Gentlemens Coats, all tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Blazon'd. To which is added an Alphabetical Table for the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy finding any name whoſe Coat is herein Blazon'd.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:61578:72"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
